hello everyone and welcome back to the
show today I'm extremely pleased to be
speaking with Chris deler Chris is a
post-doctoral fellow working in the
center for research in cognition and
neurosciences in Brussels he focuses on
computational models of cognitive
functions mental representations and
Consciousness as well as broader topics
prominent in philosophy of computation
philosophy and ethics of AI
metacognition and philosophy of science
Chris thank you ever so much for joining
me um thanks for the invitation oh it's
an absolute pleasure
um people have been asking for a bit
more of uh you know critical voices on
active inference which uh and and you're
the perfect person to go to but before
we get there uh we were talking a little
bit off air about Dan Dennett um Dan
passed away unfortunately last week at
the time of this recording I believe it
was and he was your PhD supervisor so
clearly a great deal of your work has
been influenced by Dan um I wanted to
talk about your 2015 paper um discussing
the cartisian theater and it's sort of
place or lack of you know it's it's it's
sort of ought to lack of place in
predictive processing or perhaps not but
before we go there um I know you want to
say a couple of things about Dan and it
would be great just to discuss his sort
of influence on you more more
broadly sure thank you so yeah so this
is a really sad moment because that
has I think it's easy to say defined in
large in many ways defined the the the
shape of philosophy of Mind in the 20th
century up to today and it's a really
great loss to to see him go um and I I
guess I I mentioned to you when we were
setting up this meeting that I would
like to spend a little bit of time
discussing him
because uh I think that Dan is in some
ways uh a kind of a philosopher who
should
be uh followed in the way that he
approached philosophy of mind and uh I
think that it's you know worth focusing
on that that's that's one thing that I
find really interesting and important
about him and the other thing is that uh
I had a personal relationship with him
uh I did two extended research stays
with him during my PhD and we've met at
many occasions at different
conferences uh and uh over the past
weekend there were a lot of
obituaries uh that that showed up about
Dan and uh he clearly was a lot of
things to many people and it's actually
astonishing to see how many people he
has influenced across multiple
disciplines but I think it's also worth
remembering uh that he was just an
extremely
kind uh nice guy he was just a he was
just a joy to to be
around um and so that's the second thing
that I sometimes feel is missing from
contemporary philosophy so so the way he
did philosophy is that he tended to
focus on science right and he thought
that there's no philosophy free
science uh and similarly he thought that
that philosophy of Mind should be
informed by uh our best state of
scientific
knowledge and sometimes I feel
philosophers forget that it's very easy
to uh stay within the boundaries of our
discipline and and not reach out uh and
not try to to you know have a peak
what's going outside of the boundaries
of the Ivory Tower of philosophy of mind
and I think it's really important to
remember that that it that you know that
if there's a legacy to Dan's work it's
that philosophy can be informed by
science and it's actually very
productive and important for
philosophers to engage with scientists
and it's a kind of a two-way it's a
two-way uh exchange of ideas where both
sides can benefit
productively um and then the second
thing is that philosophers can be
extremely serious about themselves and
about their work and about really
entrenched in their positions and and uh
very
competive uh and uh yeah kind of
hardheaded and I think that
Dan uh although we cannot say that he
had a small
personality he was definitely uh you
know a flamboyant personality as well
but he he was really a person who was
very kind towards Junior Scholars he was
he would always find time to engage with
with uh younger researchers and
students he was very curious of what
other people might say about his work
even if it was
critical and uh he did not take himself
entirely seriously and I think this is
something that's also worth remembering
right so he he was happy to sometimes
concede that maybe he didn't think
something
through uh and uh he thought that first
philosophy first and foremost should be
a great intellectual adventure and not
some kind of
dogmatic holy war and I think that's
that's something worth remembering I
don't know if you would like to ask
anything else about Dan or well I um
yeah I mean firstly to Echo everything
you just said I mean I never met Dan um
I guess I'm I'm not currently at that
place in my career where that would have
been viable I mean um I only left school
what you know uh in
2017 but you know even studying
philosophy at school Dan's name was
pervasive right I mean interestingly
pervasive across sure philosophy of mind
which we studied but even qu you know
broader questions of epistemology um an
ontology Dan's name would come up in a
way that other philosophers wouldn't and
so he always seemed like a kind of
Grandfather of modern
philosophy in you know and so he's one
of for me one of the sort of icons who
I've never met and I've never SP spoken
with but are incredibly influential even
if as you say not I don't agree
necessarily with everything I think Dan
thinks or thought but yeah incredibly
important um and you're absolutely right
I mean just being on Twitter or X or
whatever this weekend it was
unbelievable I I mean maybe in some ways
this is just because I I follow so many
academics but just the timeline was
absolutely replete with with uh
obituaries and condolences and it was
quite remarkable so clearly he touched a
lot of people um both as a human being
and also as an
intellect yeah I'm curious what was he
what was he like sort of during your PhD
uh I mean I guess this is a personal
question because I that's what I want to
be embarking on you know this year but
what was he sort of like as a as a guide
and a mentor so he was
extremely uh kind as I said before so
so uh very encouraging he was eager to
learn so something that I've heard from
other people who have done post
appointments with him or have been his
PhD students in the past was that when
someone came to him with an next with a
expertise in a field that he wasn't very
familiar with he was really eager to
learn uh from them so so when I was
working on my dissertation which was on
predictive
processing um and that was a new topic
back then um he was very interested in
learning about the models and And
discussing with me formal papers right
about about different modeling
algorithms for example which was super
nice yeah um and one thing that was
really special about him as a as an
academic Mentor was that he was uh
extremely well-rounded so I feel that
today in Academia I mean it's not a
product of the last 10 years but you
know we we we've we have very narrow
focuses we we we value
specialization and then explored
everything so a lot of people don't
remember this about him but he was able
to code for example he has done work
with programming in the past uh he was
very skilled in many domains and that
would often come back because his
curiosity and his abilities in in
multiple areas
would allow him to draw connections
between different fields of work so so
he was very quick in suggesting readings
for example that you wouldn't get as
standard recommendations from people
working on a particular topic because
they would be off they would often seem
like they are very removed from what
you're interested in but later on you
would follow up and you would find out
that there are actually connections
between these ideas and that certain
ideas surfaced in many different places
in many different disciplines in
Academia over time in different guises
so that was extremely
valuable uh and yeah he was just uh he
was just fun to be around so he was
obviously very busy he was still quite
generous with his time despite how many
appointments he had and how many people
were always kind of you know fighting
for his attention and trying to to to
get a bit of his time uh but one of the
best pieces of advice I ever got from
him was when I was visiting him and I
was writing on writing a paper I was
working on a paper and as I was halfway
through this paper I don't know three
quarters in someone else published a
paper that was extremely similar to my
paper to the point where I kind of
thought okay I have to abandon this
project because there's no way to
publish this right now because it's just
too
similar and I was pissed I was irritated
I was kind of you know I can
imagine I sunk a lot of time into that
project and I went to him and I said
yeah I'm I'm pissed this this just
happened what am I supposed to
do uh and he said to me something that I
try to remember every time you know I
feel scooped by someone with a paper or
or
um someone is publishing like crazy on
some topic that I'm interested in and I
don't have I don't feel like I can catch
up sometimes uh with the literature
which has happened with predictive
processing quite a bit my PhD uh because
that literature exploded at the time but
he told me this he said philosophers
arguing about who came up with an idea
first are like sailors wabbling over who
was the first one to notice that the
wind has
changed and I thought that's that's very
good advice
because the reason we all got into
philosophy wasn't probably because you
know we wanted to
be uh a superstar of philosophy it isn't
because we hopefully it isn't because we
have humongous Egos and we think that we
are right and everyone else is wrong but
it's just because we appreciated
thinking about certain
problems and it's in at the end of the
day it's a collaborative Endeavor and uh
you know science philosophy
uh building knowledge is is a project
where which in which we should engage
collaboratively and despite being a
giant that he was he was also then I
mean he was always very uh
uh in his writings and in in talking to
him he was always very much against the
idea of a singular genius so this this
idea which philosophy often suffers from
even today this myth of a you know
single author that can lift a whole
field it's a bit ironic that Dan was the
person who was against this idea given
how much influence he had over the field
but he and this is visible in several of
his books and writings he didn't like
this idea a singular genius he thought
that you know really certain
ideas uh start to kind of Brew in in in
in the right conditions and then there's
just someone who who who makes the
discovery or who catches wind of what's
happening but he always thought of
himself as standing on the shoulders of
giants like
Quin uh and and and other people so yeah
yeah that's a beautiful question qu it
makes me think there's a there's one by
KL young where he says people don't have
ideas ideas have
people yeah Yung was thinking about in a
slightly different way than Dan was but
it's um you know in in some
psychoanalytic manner but the the sort
of sentiment is the
same yes and it's actually some it's
extremely close to some of the ideas
that he presented in from bacteria to B
and back so so when he talks in the
chapters where he talks about memes yeah
it sometimes goes extremely close to to
that line of thinking that uh we I
was doing my first research stay when he
was finishing that book and I had a
privilege of of uh going through the
drafts And discussing the drafts with
him and Martin bowry who was a post at
the time with him also a visiting post
do and uh I remember that we s one
evening and we had this conversation
where we picked a passage from the book
from the chapter about memes and we said
Dan it's what are you sure this is this
is what you want to say here because it
starts to sound
like humans are just you know material
vehicles for memes and is this it sounds
very extreme and I remember he was
sitting there quietly for a second
thinking and he said you know what maybe
you're right maybe my Pros got the
better of me
so um yeah so so to say right people
always uh praised him for his Pros right
um famously are kind of
very well praic is a derogatory word but
I mean it here in a in a sort of
praiseworthy way that you some
philosophy is very snooze worthy let's
be honest uh but you know the things
that I read of Dan are certainly not and
that itself is quite remarkable um you
know the ideas aside of course which are
very potent and influential to be able
to write about something otherwise
deeply complex and otherwise for you
know a certain audience extremely boring
and to make that come alive is an
incredible skill in of
itself I yeah go ahead I just wanted to
say on that point that I completely
agree with you and uh he definitely had
his own voice as a writer which was
remarkably close to the way he would
speak in
conversations uh but what's really
interesting is that that way of writing
that he introduced into
philosophy uh it was it it it gained
praise over time I think late in
especially in his later years but
initially it was a bit of a problem for
him so when he wrote his first book
content and Consciousness which I
believe came out in 1969
that book got some negative reviews
because of the way in which it was
written and it wasn't a
fully actualized denian narrative yet uh
but you could still get some you know of
his uh his kind of Massachusetts
sensibilities in there and and what was
really interesting is that uh some
people really
uh recoiled from that style of writing
at the
time well I think um yes I I sense
there's been a change in that right I
mean the the underlying soci
sociological reasons for why that's the
case whether it is just uh people
copying someone like Dan is an open
question but I do think that um well
Duty might be a strong word but we have
a we we do have an obligation in some
sense to make our works leg
right uh even if it's not for the L
audience even if it's being published in
philosophy journals we can't be talking
into you know this the N of one um you
know V chamber that is just our own mind
and Dan again of the stuff I read from
and also his contemporaries uh people
like Ned L and and David Charmers and
then some of my favorites you know Evan
Thompson who I know was a postto with
Dan it's it's fun to read um and it
makes people like me want to do
philosophy and again this is no shot at
anyone who was working 120 years ago
whose Pros might make you want to fall
asleep but um I yeah I guess there's a
broader broader thing there that um we
do have a we do have a duty to transmit
our ideas in a legible intelligible
Manner and Dan epitomize that definitely
and he was also I mean he was also a he
had the style of his own which was very
entertaining which I think is another
thing yeah a lot of a lot of academics
could learn from him uh he's not the
only example of that
um but but of of of you know of being
able to write in an entertaining way
while also transmitting very complex
ideas but
uh yeah I like this idea of an author
having their own style you know um I
think Carl is one of them I mean it's
fitting that we on this podcast right I
mean um I've been accused at certain
points in my writing of writing in
frisan E I love I love review's comments
where they mention Frist e because I
can't help you know having read so much
of frist's work of Carl's work I can't
help but use the word
evince yeah that's definitely that's I
feel like it's a bit of a dog whistle
you know it's a if if someone uses the
word evince in their paper especially
when you're reviewing a paper you can
see who they've been reading uh a lot so
so I feel like evince is this kind of
Mark of of someone who has read a lot of
friston if EV appears in your own
writings it might be because you've been
reading a lot of friston and moving away
from Dan a little bit and and towards
what you wanted to talk about in terms
of papers I reread some of my older
papers for this meeting because you know
some of them are seven years old and I
don't remember what I wrote there
uh I was yeah definitely it's a journey
for me as a non-native speaker to
develop some kind of style and and I I
read some of the sentences I wrote in
the past and I wouldn't put those ideas
in that way today but you know well I've
got to say that I didn't have that
impression um the one I read I think it
was yesterday was the The Curtain Call
for the cartisian theater which was 2015
which feels I mean like yeah I was doing
my GCS for people in England you know I
was doing my sort of I was 16 or
whatever but um I didn't feel that way
at all and and clearly there's a lot of
denti and influence there in in that
paper but what I like about it I was
going to say this in reference to Dan is
you know you mentioned his kind of
openness his curiosity his epistemic
humility fundamentally you know I mean
we don't know with with a lot of things
in life we really don't know and that's
the beauty I mean we would all be out of
jobs if we knew and life itself you know
there would be no information transfer
arguably there would be no life at least
worth living um and I felt that in that
paper you very much evinced if you
pardon me the word a great deal of
epistemic humility which I really liked
I mean it you know you're critiquing the
Frisian in this case the Frisian hsian
model of Hobson model of um their their
sort of invocation of the cartisian
theater and what Dan called cartisian
materialism when it comes to I believe
you call it action orientated predictive
processing but I guess we call it active
inference now
yes but you know you didn't say but this
is the this is the fundamental way in
which Consciousness appears or this is
the way the the representations work so
I enjoyed that I mean for people who
haven't read that paper what and again
it comes back to Dan what is cartisian
materialism um what kind of role does it
have to play in terms of predictive
processing and then what's the what's
the problem with it you know okay uh
nice so we're really starting at the
beginning so that's a paper uh me and my
good friend Joe with whom I studied in
edenburgh before starting my PhD uh we
studied in edenburgh uh where we read a
draft of Andy Clark's surfing
uncertainty and one of our Master
seminars wow and that's how we got into
predictive
processing um so so that's a paper we
wrote early on and it was a kind of a
knee-jerk reaction to a paper by Carl
friston and uh Hopson yeah H in which
they invoked the notion of cartisian
theater so cartisian
materialism is this term that was coined
by Dan dennet to describe a certain view
of Consciousness which he thought was
very a kind of a residue from the from
the ideas of daycard and you know the
idea that there's a certain point in the
brain where information needs to reach
and then it somehow needs to be rendered
in the medium of Consciousness so for
for decart that was of course the pineal
gland which was this point of
interaction between a mechanistic
mind uh and the soul and there was a
there was a certain in his view of the
mind and his of the brain also
uh there were these uh humors right
there were these uh different liquids in
the brain that would create pressures on
the on the pineal gland and depending on
which part of the pineal gland they
would put pressure on there would be a
certain
experience that would uh appear in in in
the soul in in
Consciousness uh so so what denet
criticized about this view of
Consciousness is that it requires a
certain type of double trans
transduction he called it so it's not
only that there's sense it's not only
that there are forces impinging on our
sensory periphery from the environment
which are then transduced into the
medium of neuronal spikes and you know
um hormone secretions and so on all the
things that are happening
mechanistically in the brain but then it
seems to imply that there's a certain
point in which in the processing of
information where
the medium information needs to be
transduced again from the medium of
neuronal spikes and all the
mechanistic um happenings in the brain
into the medium of Consciousness so he
sometimes referred this this this the
product or the this this
this substance of the second transaction
he called it figment right with with by
analogy with pigment so figment is this
thing that needs to be put on to your
you know onto your representations of
the world in order to imbue them with
qualitative properties because
presumably as most dualists and and
non-reductive physicalists would tell us
there are phenomenal properties and
there are dispositional or functional
properties and these are two different
types of properties right
so all anti-reductionists about
Consciousness will claim that phenomenal
properties are not reducible to
functional properties and then said well
if that's the case then it seems to
be then we end up with this picture of
the Mind where information hits the
retina let's say in the case of
vision it's transduced into the medium
of neuronal spikes that information is
those neuronal spikes are propagated
into through the cortical hierarchies
and then we have to ask where is this
point in the brain where
we put on the figment onto the onto the
visual information right so so it seems
like we need to apply the mental paint
as block would put it again even though
I would like to say that here as I'm
talking about mental paint that's a
slight abuse of the term as block uses
it but the point is that you need to you
seem to require adding
something into into the workings of the
brain in order to render information
consciously
information conscious and that's
something that he really wanted to
reject so his
point uh wasn't that there's
a his point wasn't that there's there
there cannot be some aspect of the brain
which is privileged in terms of bringing
about conscious
experience H it's rather that there's
nothing extra in ter metaphysically
extra or ontolog ically extra added into
the
information when it becomes conscious
right it's just that you have you
process information
unconsciously and then it can become
conscious at any particular time uh
given that it was processed enough
through the cical hierarchy and so on
right so so there's no mysterious
properties that need to be applied again
or added back into the into the
information that is being processed by
the physical system so he very much so
the name cartisian Mater materialism is
supposed to suggest that there's a there
there's a materialist picture of the
brain but there's this much like in the
case of the pineal gland in in the case
of thearts dualism in cartisian
materialism there's a particular
location in the brain that information
needs to reach in order to become
conscious and this and this particular
Center in the brain is this one area
that serves as the cartisian
theater kind of as a as a place where
which serves as the screen of
Consciousness right and that's something
that he wanted to reject because he
believed that there's no one particular
place in the brain where information
needs to be processed in order to for it
to be conscious it's rather that there's
a collection of different functions that
need to be in place simultaneously
trading information in order for
information to be conscious right and
that's also why in many disorders of
Consciousness such as I don't know
visual form
agnosia uh or blindsight we see that
conscious experience underg goes a kind
of graceful degradation where people
lose certain aspects of conscious
experience uh but that doesn't mean that
they are render somehow entirely
unconscious or something like that right
it's it's rather that you can knock out
different modules if you want to talk
about about that in this those ways are
different systems out but as long as
there's some kind of wider Comm of
information going on throughout the
brain Consciousness is still in place so
I feel like the rebuttal to this would
be the argument that okay I guess the
cartisian theater in some ways has
multiple reference in the sense that one
thinks of as you say the screen of
Consciousness I mean the word theater
brings that to mind very vividly
uh and one thinks also of the homunculus
who's watching the the screen and this
sort of little man who's watching and
and that's obviously got a number of
problems most strikingly the infinite
regress of the homunculus but then one
but then there's also this separate more
mechanistic point about the locus of
Consciousness and this sort of singular
physical point I guess the rebuttal to
that would be well even if you adopt a
more distributed idea of the brain as a
network and you're talking more in terms
of functional connections there still
seems to be either you know either we're
saying well there is no
consciousness well let's disparage with
that just for the meantime but let's say
there is consciousness well we don't
want to say that necessarily the sound
waves or the visual information itself
is conscious so there does seem to be a
transduction at some point from matter
into phenomenal space now that sounds
like to me that there needs to be a
moment at which just by necessity that
information enters into you know in
metaphorical use that phenomenal space
now it might not be the case that that's
the same for every experience it might
not be the same that it's always it
might not be that it's the case it's the
same in every place for you know for
every experience but it does seem to be
this case that even in a diverse range
of networks there is a moment at which
the lights come on so to speak would Dan
or yourself have a problem with that
weaker form of the cartisian materialism
or cartisian theater
um all right so that's a good question
that's you're pinpointing exactly the
the the main issue so
so
um
Dan I think would have a problem with
that because especially so so he
explicitly wanted
to uh leave behind this metaphor of a
screen mhm or this metaphor of uh you
know know some kind of special
properties in in Consciousness so a lot
of people attack him these days for
being an eliminativist about
Consciousness and he was very adamant
that he's not in that camp precisely
because he would always claim you know
there is something it is like to be Dan
dennet and it's different from what it's
like to be me and it's different from
what it's like to be you so there is a
subjective perspective on the world that
you have that is that is different from
mine and that was different from
his uh and uh so he didn't want to deny
that but he wanted to change the way we
speak about these things so so this is
why he together with Kei Frankish they
coined the term
illusionism because they wanted to to
stop talking about phenomenal properties
as things that we have
to uh find a place for in our
ontology now
uh yeah so that's that's one thing and I
think that he would also have a bit of a
problem with that because uh of his
multiple drafts model so so his idea was
that you know he was very much informed
by uh bars and thean and the GL the work
on global workspace so this idea that
there's
this there is this there are these
longterm long range projections sorry
long range projections in the braak
which connect different areas and
there's a kind of exchange of
information going on but on his view of
Consciousness there isn't one particular
system that is the Consciousness system
right so so it's it's likely that I
think he would agree with the claim that
a weak claim that there is a number of
fun cognitive functions that need to be
in place in order to for something to
have Consciousness like ours or
sufficiently similar to
hours um but I think he would reject
the uh the claim that any one of these
systems is somehow privileged over the
others that's that's one thing and then
the multiple drafts idea is that there
are multiple competing streams of
information in all of these systems that
are necessary for
Consciousness and which stream
you're conscious of which stream of uh
you're experiencing is kind of up
to one the the the how much Cloud it has
in the system so how strong how much
control it has over over the rest of the
of the cognitive economy what he kinded
as Fame in the brain and then the other
thing is the kind of probes that you
encounter so so kind of uh either
external um external situations which
which or stimulite that that that
require solicit a certain response from
you or internal probes like you know if
you're if you're sitting there and
you're really thinking about your uh ex
or if you're really thinking about the
EXP focusing trying to be mindful about
the experience of eating an apple that's
also a way of privileging certain
streams of sensory information or or
memory traces over other streams of
information in the in the brain
um and so okay so that's I think what he
would want to say probably about this
now for me I guess I'm
less uh I'm less
uh convinced of of you know I I I like
the multiple drafts model but I'm not
completely on
board uh because a lot of the work in
science of Consciousness these days
focuses on uh on higher order systems on
this division between lower order
systems and higher or lower order
processing and higher order processing
metacognition um and I think
that I'm leaning more towards some kind
of higher order theory of Mind these
days and I do think that there is a
there might be a certain
privileged set of processes or systems
that are are are necessary and in some
sense they
might that they're not exactly I
wouldn't want to slide back into
cartisian materialism by saying like oh
information needs to go there in order
to be conscious but they do play an
important functional role um and I think
that because I I I subscribe to some
version of the higher order View I think
that means that I have to be a little
bit weaker on the cartisian
materialist criti critique this these
days because there is a certain I do
separate the system into two levels and
where one level is seems to be
privileged over the other in terms of uh
the role it plays in bringing about
Consciousness okay cool we can go there
that's that's that's an interesting
development because um I'm so I'm aware
of these higher older theories of
Consciousness with respect to
self-awareness so as you know there are
these
so-called uh pre-reflective states of um
self-awareness or self a subject which
you can sort of deflate just a
subjectivity let's say and the whole the
whole principle of these you know
phenomenologically and ontologically is
that no one there is nothing that is
aware of them they offer the uh texture
the background to uh the objects of
Consciousness but they never areed into
an tentional object obviously his work
goes back to S ponti H and so on now uh
this kind of poses an issue for the
higher order theories of Consciousness
because for them these states or or or
these experiences which in turn are not
reflected upon they well it seems a bit
problematic because they propose that
actually there are higher order states
which take these conscious uh these
pre-reflective states as their object so
there is no such thing as the pre- Ive
or non-reflective self-awareness rather
it's sort of hidden hidden uh these
higher order uh intentional as are
hidden from us and then the rebuttal
comes and says well how you know how are
these not conscious right like surely I
should be aware of these higher order
states which have as their object my
pre-reflective states of self-awareness
and the higher order Consciousness
theorist come along and say Well they're
not conscious uh and they intend the
pre-re states of self awareness without
themselves being conscious and then you
have just the ontological question well
how does that work and so I guess the
question would be we seem to have these
it doesn't have to be self-awareness we
seem to have these uh phenomenal I guess
the word coming to mind again is
textures right I mean what people
traditionally would have called qual or
Quail which is sort of um what you know
seems to constitute the what it is
likeness of Consciousness so the redness
of red or the APPL of eating an apple
and so on and
um these seem to be constituative of my
experience even if I don't necessarily
have to rify them and that's the same
with sort of the my own subjectivity or
my own intentionality how do you as a
kind of leaning towards a higher order
Theory Of Consciousness how do you deal
with these otherwise seemingly
irreducible ineffable intrinsic features
which at least on the surface seems to
seem to
Bell um becoming an intentional object a
sort of overt reflective
object uh all right wow uh that I'm no
no no no no that's that's that's a good
question um so I must say that I'm not
that familiar with the literature on the
pre-reflective uh self-consciousness I'm
I'm I'm getting more into it because I
was recently interested my my recent
work is more interested in affect and
effective experiences so that's what I
work on in Brussels now and some people
postulate that for example in order to
have emotional experiences you need to
have
a an explicit involvement of the self
yeah so jolu for example is a higher
order theorist who claims that in order
to undergo an emotional experience you
not only need to activate what he calls
an emotional
schema uh which
conceptualizes your the the sub uh
subcortical processing in the amigaland
and so on but also you need to have an
active self schema so you kind of his
big big catchphrases no self no emotion
so unless you you are aware that it's to
you that something is scary then you
just don't feel fear right previously he
call like the
smaller uh claim was no self no fear so
you can only fear something if you
realize that is dangerous to you or or
you you fear um that thing that object
so so I'm not yet that familiar with
that literature and I know also that
even if we leave the self aside there's
this whole literature on minimal
phenomenal experiences which is
something that Thomas metzinger is now
very interested in
um precisely because in deep meditative
State you can let go of the of the self
right and and you can presumably have
these pure phenomenal
experiences uh which are
supposedly uh relaxing this idea that
there's a self which is the the the
anchor for the point of view on the
world um and I think that you're right
that
both uh minimal
pre-reflective uh experiences uh this
this and and minimal phenomenal States
they they do put pressure on on higher
order theorists and so I think that
there's two ways in which we can respond
so so one way is I think the way that
would be taken by someone like David
rosenal so David rosenal talks about
qualitative
spaces and he very much wants
to uh wants
to uh
reclaim the word qualitative property
from the hands of of strong phenomenal
realists and say look there's nothing
mysterious about qualitative properties
as such qualitative properties as such
are not uh some kind of mysterious
properties they're just we know about
qualitative properties we talk about
qualitative properties in science and we
can think of the brain as representing
qualitative properties that's not the
problem regular scientifically
understood qualitative properties are
not problematic on their own in in in a
deeper metaphysical way unless you
conflate them with qualia which are
supposed to be not only qualitative but
also you
know they're supposed to be ineffable
they're supposed to be private and so on
intrinsic and so on and so forth so what
he's trying trying to do is he's trying
to separate the notion of qualit
qualitative property from the notion of
intrinsic property and once you do that
you can actually claim that on the first
level you will have representations of
qualitative properties and then you need
this kind of higher order process that
targets or picks out or re- represents
depending who you are these lower order
States in order to have qualitative
experiences and that's that's one way
you can go about it I agree that this
might not be satisfying to you because
the problem then is well okay so what
about these states where we seemly
undergo
ego uh dissolution and and where the
self seemingly doesn't play any role it
seems to me that in those
cases traditional higher order theorists
will have to claim that well you're kind
of in a under an illusion that there's
no that there's no self perhaps The
Narrative self Falls away but there
might be this kind of minimal notion of
a self that's still in place for example
presumably if you're in a deep
meditative State uh you're still
deploying your attention in some way or
controlling your attention in some way
there's some kind of process of
attentional monitoring
happening and the system which is
controlling the the the allocation or
the flow of attention if you want to
call it that that's the system which is
actually responsible for for this
minimal self that's where the minimal
self resides and and Michael graciano as
you probably know has built a whole view
of Consciousness around the idea that
the control model for attention is the
the the the the representation that we
introspect when we're thinking when
we're experiencing things and then the
second way so that's one way to do it
the other way would be to say well how
many higher order levels are there right
so you can always this is a you
know it's as much of an objection as a
as an argument in favor right so you can
always claim that there's an extra level
of representation and it's not that
things have to be represented on the
second level there's a higher level and
so for example in graciano's model to go
back to that as I understand his picture
these days we have have some first order
perceptual or or other
processes uh then we have the
attentional model which we represents
these systems in a kind of uh way where
they are
distorted uh and then we when we
introspect there's actually a higher
order model yet that is picking out the
contents of the attentional control
model uh at least that's one way to
understand his claim and so in that
picture we would have this kind of of
three layers uh of of the higher order
model right so it could then we would we
could claim for example that when we're
having these pure minimal
experiences that the higher the higher
level that this introspective level
which which renders things as for me
experiences is dropping out but the
control model again is still there in
place and so what we're experiencing is
just these representations in the
control model but there's no explicit
level of introspection so the self is
kind of sidelined I'm kind of
spitballing here right now no so so was
I to be fair because as I said I'm not
uh first of all I don't have a complete
Theory Of
Consciousness and I would be I hope the
last person to claim that maybe one day
uh you know I will feel more confident
in claiming some piece of the cake for
me for myself sure um but but and I as I
said I'm interested in these minimal
States uh of either pre-reflective
self-awareness or minimal states of
phenomenal experience but I don't know
enough about them right now to you know
give you a very
um strong position about them yeah I
mean to be thought I was somewhat
spitballing as well I am not an expert
in higher all the theories of
Consciousness I mean I'm aware of David
Rose
and others who have proposed things akin
to a high World theories of
Consciousness right I don't really
believe in sort of Monolithic these kind
of categories right everything is sort
of everyone's got their own
idiosyncratic way of viewing these
things um I I came across it I I'm very
I am interested in pre-reflective self-a
Awareness kind of phenomenologically
more than anything I mean the
ontological metaphysical ground of it is
an interesting question I I mean just to
State my claim at least on something
like subjectivity I think there's a it's
absolutely viable to take a kind of more
San or moonan position that it's
actually just imminent it's intrinsic in
all experience even in minimal
phenomenal experiences there's still the
for
meanus and then I mean this feeds into
my kind of skepticism over higher order
theories because even in this notion of
a kind of higher order representation
there is already inbuilt into that the
for meus that is supposed to be being
represented which seems to be kind of
begging the question or you know putting
the cart before the horse
and I would again I mean this idea that
it's just intrinsic to experience and
then in some ways you're saying well
experience is intrinsic fundamentally
and there is just this
irreducibility of course that comes with
its own problems right I mean I mean how
first and foremost I mean unless you're
just a Jew list out the you know out the
can like so so no these are interesting
metaphysical questions I guess um it was
probably it was probably a bit misguided
of me to bring in the notion of qualia
because
well I guess this is an interesting
question when I was thinking about it I
was thinking about the way it sort of
pre-reflectively uh structures our
experience such that I I mean this again
I don't really know if this is true do I
need to reflect on the taste of coffee
to experience the taste of coffee in the
same sense do I need to reflect on my I
don't well seemingly phenomenologically
I don't need to reflect on myself as an
object to experience myself as a subject
um and so that's kind of why I bought in
qualia but I think probably the higher
order theories a better chance of
dealing with qualia right it's just a
representat of some represent you know
representing scheme um yes I mean these
are Dee rooted philosophical problems
that we're not going to be able to solve
on this podcast but I think an
interesting question here is um bringing
it into a basian account so you bought
you mentioned s of Fame in the brain
there uh another one of your papers s
Fame in the basian brain yeah the
question I think that comes up just to
mind is if we took denit multiple draft
models
seriously and it seems It's well in some
it seems incredibly convergent with
predictive processing and active
inference in the sense that we're
running multiple hypotheses of the
underlying cuse of our sensory
data the thing is is that we in
principle you're never reaching the kind
of infinite peak of a gussan you're
never coming up to a you know no
hypothesis in principle statistically
should occupy a one from 100% certainty
because this is just statistical
distributions right yeah if we're taking
a very Bare Bones approach to basian the
basian brain hypothesis
so I mean I've been reading this in
terms of people like Andy Clark and Kate
Nave have spoken about this kind of
seeming in the fact that perceptual
experience seems determinate orbe it
seemingly if we take the basian brain
hypothesis seriously underpinned by
indetermined probabilistic processes so
I'm curious about how one can skirt this
problem I mean Kate has her own solution
which is that Consciousness in some
sense is indeterminate although not in
the way that people naturally think of
indeterminate she thinks as a sort of
singular reality nonetheless um people
like yakob Hy will talk about
distrusting the hypothesis and so
there's this constant temporal flow I'm
curious about how you can get how you
think we can get from a predicted
processing picture of multiple h hpes
being entertained to a singular
seemingly singular coherent gal of
conscious
perception yeah that's a that's again a
very good question um so I think I would
start this by saying that
um
I don't so so I'm very much interested
in the basent brain hypothesis as a from
a kind of anti-realist stance right so
my stance towards towards these models
is kind of
um disengaged in a certain sense
ontologically so I suspend my belief in
them as actual descriptions of what's
happening in our heads yeah and I think
that uh I take this removed position of
all models are wrong some models are
useful some models are interesting uh
and I think that actually probabilistic
models have a lot going for them but
it's just one of the possible ways of
capturing what's going on in our
heads uh and so we always have to so if
you approach them from this this point
of view then then you know first of all
it relaxes a little bit your
commitment to finding the one true
solution so so you can say oh we could
model this in this way or we could model
it in that way we we make some modeling
choices that in the end determine how
we're going to think about it or how
we're going to model the behavior of the
system uh and in some ways they
are useful but in some ways they can
also be misleading right
so um so that's that's that's the kind
of to preface my my answer here so
that's the first thing uh following ing
from that one of the big decisions that
you have to make when you're deciding
how to model the basian brain If you
assume that the brain is you know doing
something like ban inference then of
course the question is how are you going
to model the process by which it's doing
it so is it we know that it's highly
unlikely that it's running exact Vision
inference uh so it needs to use some
kind of method of approximation so Carl
and people in his camp have settled on
variational ban inference as the most
likely solution here but there are other
options as well right so you could think
about sampling for example which is
another way yeah and if you had a model
based on sampling you wouldn't actually
have to be like that the problem of
determinacy is gone in many ways because
if you think that you're you know
sampling from some kind of distribution
then you're and then you're experiencing
a sample
then you're experiencing a sample it's a
determinate point and and kind of you
the information is determinant right
even though it comes from a
probabilistic distribution so that's one
way you could get around
this um the other thing that I wanted to
point out is that in uh
yacob's picture of how things work so
yakob talks about probability density
functions of
course um and uh he talks about some
kind of uh as you said uncertainty about
you know the exact uh hypothesis right
that you're entertaining because you're
never getting a kind of a pointwise
estimate you're always getting some kind
of
interval um and that's that's also a way
to go get out of it another way to get
out of it is to for example bring a
bring into the picture some kind of uh
dual coding hypothesis so you could
think that on certain levels of the
predictive hierarchy things are being
coded in continuous spaces and in others
they are discretized right so some
levels of the hierarchy are operating
on uh on probability density functions
and there are parts of the hierarchy
that are operating on probability Mass
functions okay where you can actually
pick out one hypothesis as the as the
currently winning hypothesis so the way
you the reason why you might think
that's the case is because of how
Concepts have been typically handled in
philosophy right so concepts are
supposed to be these kind of distinct
categories at least
traditionally nowadays A lot has changed
in the way we think about Concepts but
you could think that as you're bringing
something into a conceptual frame that
conceptual frame is somehow constraining
your experience so you could think that
well when I'm perceiving colors of
course the space of my color perception
is continuous but then as I'm
recognizing colors as I'm applying
certain Concepts to them I'm
discretizing my experience in certain
ways uh the problem of course with that
is that there seems to be a lot more
variety in our perceptual experience
than our conceptual appar this allows
for so we both agree on what red is but
we could find multiple examples of
objects that we would categorize as you
know we would disagree about whether
they should be categorized as red or not
right and there seems to be a lot of
perceptual experiences that fall under
the concept of redness for both of us
and we would agree that there is
variability in the in what we call in in
the experiences we would uh uh label
with the term red so so that's then a
problem
um
and I guess another option sorry I'm
kind of lay layering you know different
different ways you could think about it
and finally there's a there's another
option which is
that uh even though you have multiple
distributions that are kind of in
determinate uh or or have these kind of
intervals where where you know you're
mod modeling things with probability
Mass functions probability sorry
probability density functions so you're
you you're just picking out intervals
you might think that if you have some
process higher order process for example
that takes information from multiple
processing stages then there's a
possibility that all of this is somehow
collapsed into each other in a way where
you do get actually very narrowly
defined uh hypothesis right and again
you might think that this would happen
in some kind of discret
medium uh that doesn't have to be
connected to uh Concepts
necessarily uh so so so I think there's
plenty of ways in which you can you can
get around this problem for me
personally I think that uh nowadays I'm
actually kind of removing myself from
this this debate and I just think that
well there those are multiple ways in
which you could
model conscious experience and then and
build models of perception for example
and and and categorization of perceptual
experiences and so on and what's
interesting is really whether these
models can inform new predictions or new
hypothesis that can be tested
empirically
right yes it's uh we will come I I I we
will come to the scientific realism
versus instrumentalism thing because I'm
sure people want to hear your your take
on that
um in Greater depth it's I'm really
sorry can I can I just add one more
thing so so another reason why you just
just to kind of again just talk about
this you know why would there be one
hypothesis that's winning uh one reason
for that is nicely given by yakob Hui
and uh franches Mari in their paper I
don't 2020 I want to say I don't
remember when it came out yeah I'll have
a uh but y but they kind
of they they subscribe to kind of Jesse
Prince's view of mid levels of the
hierarchy relevant for Consciousness but
they have actually a very good answer to
why there might be you perceptual
experience and or experience in general
is not kind of indeterminate but is kind
of rather fix fixed in a certain uh
temporal window right because what's
also relevant here is that that when
we're thinking about experience we often
tend to leave out time but time is a an
a really really important aspect of our
perceptual experience and our experience
in general Consciousness in general we
know that there is a certain integration
window where you know stimuli that are
presented in the same time will be
integrated into one percept for example
so the reason they give for why there
might be a certain uh deterministic
quality to our person ctual experiences
and experience in general is
that actions are actually not
indeterminate right yeah every action
you have to take in your environment is
a kind of a determinate situation in
which you're putting your body and the
way you're changing your environment by
acting on it you're moving things around
and things kind of can either be here or
there I can lift my arm and I can lower
my arm right and I'm in between two uh
states there might be some gradation
between these two states but if I do one
thing I can every state or every action
I take or every state I put my body into
that limits my possibilities constrains
them in a in a certain way and my body
can be only in one state at a time so
when I'm performing actions when I'm
planning actions uh I need to kind of
experience the world in a way where I
don't experience myself doing five
things I'm doing one thing and that's
actually you know perhaps there were
organisms further on if we think that
the ban brain hypothesis is true perhaps
there were organisms that had a more
indeterministic experiences of the world
and presumably they would have died out
because determinacy yeah yeah exactly
that
yes yeah that's ABS that makes perfect
sense I mean again I'm I point people in
the direction of Kate nave's work as
well I mean she was just on and and she
sort of piggybacks off yakob and um
Mar's work on this uh sort of in what do
they call it sort of intermediate
processing right like these are all and
again and perfectly chimes with things
like affordances um and the fact that
perception is enslaved by action to some
degree I guess uh well multiple things
that come to mind I mean one is it seems
to me like a lot of this is uh
comes down to the question of attention
because we we make the claim that the
world is
determinate the perceptual world is
determinant but I would propose and
again this is riding off what Kate
thinks that the world is determinant in
the very sort of focalized purview of my
determinate world now if I have if I'm
looking at my periphery it is not
determinate at all and I think if to
also build onto this action-based
picture it's because I can only really I
only really Act on what I pay attention
to so do you think it's viable to say
that you know you're talking about this
higher order process which collapses the
um probabilistic densities into a kind
of you know we can think of it doing
kind of a direct Delta function it just
like collaps it into a single
value is how much of that would be that
that is actually just ATT tension right
that higher order process is
attentionally homing in on a singular
you know derives a singular per
and then we can say well that's because
attention is in many ways the slave of
action I think that's very plausible so
this is more less The View that we
defended with Joe in the fame in the
brain paper right so so we kind of put
attention in the in the Forefront of
Consciousness there uh this is also a
view s i I defended a similar view in my
dissertation uh and I do think that
attention is extremely important for for
Consciousness and know yakob actually
also thinks that right so he points out
that on predictive or or the active
inference stories about uh the
brain uh Consciousness cannot be
entirely separated from attention
because attention is precision
optimization right and precision
optimization or expected Precision
optimization happens on multiple stages
in the system happens on multiple stages
of the processing stages of the system
simultaneously MH so so there's I really
there's never a time where the
attentional mechanism is completely off
so to speak in the brain there's always
some kind of biasing attentional biasing
in terms of uh expected Precision way
weighing of of uh error prediction
errors happening somewhere in the system
so attention seems to be necessary for
Consciousness at least on on the on the
active inference predictive processing
story uh so yeah I I find Kate's
suggestion
uh very palatable how much does this um
feed into broader questions of
agency um teleology if you want to go
all the way there and and and relevance
I mean I'm interested in theories of
relevance or relevance realization John
BVI this kind of idea and the idea
attention in many ways is the kind of
driver or or the product of a organism
which needs to uh you know inact
relevance realization it needs to be
able to disambiguate that which is
relevant to it and that which is
irrelevant to it and that I think I I've
made this argument I wrote this paper
it's um currently in review about how I
think that attention is ultimately the
slave of preferences and I think you
could say attention is and that means
that attention is ultimately slave of
relevance because you know I it's not
random what I pay attention to obviously
and also the very fact that I can pay
attention is is itself a prior an act of
prioritization it takes a kind of
flattened world and creates peaks of
saliens yeah so how much do you think
that we can build in values
relevance meaning and so on into this
kind of more strip back mechanistic
perceptual
picture that's a really nice question
and if you don't mind I would like to
read that draft if you don't mind to
because this is something that I'm
working on now in Brussel with Axel
Claremont and actually Axel has done
some research years ago on attention and
salience in addicts so he has
shown he and other people that his Co
authors they've shown that there is so
so attention is driven by preferences as
you said in the sense that addicts do
pay more attention to things that are
triggering their addiction right so you
know if you're a gambling addict and I
show you pictures of uh poker chips or
cards those are much more Salient to you
than kind of neutral stimuli right right
right right uh so so so that's the the
first point so so I think you're on to
something there and I I just want to
also say that yeah that's proba like
this is this is um evidence coming from
humans but if we go to a much more basic
level I think that attention is doing
basically prioritizing certain
information streams over other
information streams yeah um and what
that means is just as you
said organisms that have attention are
probably organisms that live in envir en
Ms complex enough where they have to do
some kind of motivational tradeoffs or
they have to tradeoff acting on one
piece of information against another
piece of information right so there
there there seems to be attending to one
stimulus against another stimulus so you
have to
prioritize what you're going to do and
so if attention is in the business of
prioritizing processing of or trading
off processing of certain things over
other things then that's exactly very
similar to motivational tradeoffs right
where you're you're responding to a
certain stimulus over another
stimulus uh because you know even though
one stimulus for example will yield you
rewards immediately another stimulus
will yield you greater rewards in in a
in a window of remove time so so you
have and and these two things seem to be
quite connected in a sense that if you
want to apply yourself to you know
pursue a stimulus that will yield
greater rewards that are removed in time
it seems that it would be useful if you
had a some kind of a very riment perhaps
system of prioritizing information about
that
stimulus and kind of making you direct
yourself away from the from the
immediately rewarding stimulus right
yeah and I think these things are
extremely connected and in fact if we
look at the literature on addiction and
evidence that comes from rodents so
so uh work of people like Kent parage on
mice the main driver of what they call
incentive salience so so what has been
labeled in the literature as the wanting
signals so signals which which uh code
prefer the preference for stimuli um or
the drive for certain stimuli the these
uh these signals have been linked to
dopamine which has also been linked to
to attentional control at least in
humans and and other mammals so
Precision right exactly exactly so I
think that there's a there's there's a
lot
of uh there's a very strong relationship
here uh between these between attention
and some kind of uh I'm not sure I I
always worry about the word preference
because I worry that people will
misunderstand yeah what we mean mean by
that because when scientists work
scientists working on reinforcement
learning or you know rodents or or uh
some kind of simple animals they talk
about preference it's clear that they're
talking about
preferences uh but they don't talk about
some kind of conscious yeah intentional
States uh the way we think of them in
everyday life and I sometimes worry that
especially in philosophy of Mind where
people people often come from this
armchair position where they think first
about how things seem to them uh from
the first person perspective for example
and then they they they look at the
empirical evidence I sometimes worry
that there might be some confusion and I
also I'm a little bit uh squeamish about
talking about meaning here because I
think that meaning is a very big
word um so so I I really like this term
incentive salience because I think it's
it's connects precisely what you're
interested in which is salience so the
fact that some stimulus is Salient to an
organism with the the the idea of an
incentive so the the idea that the
reason why it's Salient is because it is
associated by the organism with some
expected reward and that's what's
driving the organism's
Behavior behavior and also I mean inert
and overt Behavior so paying attention
to something might be a kind of of you
know uh covert uh Behavior right yeah
yeah yeah considered conceptualized as a
kind of covert Behavior right yeah I I
certainly view it as such a sort of
mental action uh yeah exactly down
exactly the same sort of um prob you
know the same base graph if you wanted
to you know the same c and e Matrix if
you wanted to uh yeah so there's plenty
of things out I mean one is you're
absolutely right I think it needs to you
know we always need to say we're talking
about preferences in the basian belief
sense of that neurons have preferences
the atoms have preferences but they they
have basian preferences they have
attractor sets they have so on or at
least they look as it they can be
described as if and so on and we've had
this and we'll we can come to this of
course um when I talk about meaning the
reason why I do so is because I think
the the way that preferences in slave
action is is encoded in a hierarchically
deep fashion such that you know the
certain things that we can claim have uh
make our lives meaningful are those
which seem to have this trickle down
effect such that they one way of
thinking about it is in terms of meta
stability you know the the sort of the
deepest wells in which the other
attractor Wells are kind of subsumed so
I've been thinking about this in terms
of okay you know maybe my ultimate you
know what makes my life meaningful is
you know for evolutionary reasons is
being a social adaptive member of
society now what I pay attention to
although it's indirect and and implicit
and covert is often a manifestation of
that so why am you know why am I writing
a paper because I want to get a PhD why
I don't I want to get a PhD because I
want people to think I'm impressive what
and eventually in some sort of
Aristotelian fashion you ground out for
me in these kind of hyper priors which
seem to have this kind of deep
filtration into our very low-level
attentional schema one question that
I've been thinking about as a kind of
followup is I think it's very reasonable
to say that you know when I'm
hungry because it's a very deep rooted
prior it kind of has a a standardly high
Precision waiting that prior such that
if when there's
deviation well maybe not maybe it's a um
when there's deviation from that prior
there's an action policy that grants it
high Precision waiting I should say
because we're not always hungry or aware
of our hunger levels so there's a slight
Nuance there um but you know we can just
say that it's a you know for lack of a
better word it's kind of an import deep
prior MH I think it's fair to say that
when that's the case I'm obviously I'm
far more drawn to food right of course
I'm drawn to the fridge I'm drawn to
adverts of food now but I've been
thinking is that is it the case
therefore that preferences and and that
which is afforded in terms of basing
preferences or high Precision weight at
that moment literally change our
perception in such a way as it's sort of
like a sapier Warf hypothesis for V for
perception or is it the case that our
perception is uniform and what ends up
happening of course our attention isn't
uniform but our perception is uniform
and what ends up happening is we kind of
overlay uh our perception with the kind
of conceptual schema and well also kind
of the attentional schema but actually
in the sort of fundamental aspects the
intrinsic aspects of our experience uh
the colors the sounds and so on things
remain the same
have you got any kind of intuition on
that
question uh this is a good question
because I think uh so so I'm kind of
torn on this on this question so so if
you're looking at these hierarchical if
you're thinking in terms of these
hierarchical basan models and you know
active inference where there's cascading
predictions constraining the activity on
the levels below it seems like there
should be some form of influence of you
know your Global States for example over
your local States right so so being
hungry is a kind of a state of
deprivation which seems to be a kind of
a state
which is I would I would maybe label it
as a global state in the sense that it
pertains to your organismic functions
and if it's not satisfied you will
eventually die right so so it's kind of
a a Glo a state of global importance to
the to the cognitive system so to speak
because it it's it's the existence of
the cognitive system is contingent on
on uh on keeping that state within
certain bounds
so and then there's a question of like
whether there's a way in which through
as you said saliency maps and
attentional modulation and all these
things and as you said conceptual
overlay for example there's a
possibility in which
this higher order well let's call it
Global State again would constrain the
space of possible hypotheses or possible
models in such a way that it would have
determinate effect on your conscious
experience um and I think it definitely
can have an effect on your conscious
experience overall because if you think
of your effective experiences yeah you
know we have the term hangry which
clearly
indicates that you can your effective
state is changing and and you can go
into a certain mood because you're in
this Global state of deprivation and
then your your fuse gets shorter and you
get irritable and so on whether it
changes your perceptual
States I think that under some models
people should be committed to claiming
that it
does I am not so sure about that because
this is and and then we're here getting
to the to the second kind of uh part of
this dilemma for me because there's this
whole literature about cognitive
penetrability and whether our beliefs
influence how we perceive the world
qualitatively whether they beliefs
influence perception and from my
understanding um for example the work of
Chess firest Stone and Brian Shaw the
evidence for that is very very limited
yeah so it seems that our beliefs can
for example influence our actions very
easily yeah but they do not change our
perception as readily as uh it might
seem intuitive and so here I would
probably try to be a little bit cautious
and now with one curve yet and that's
that's something that I'm working on now
which is this um the effective ladness
of
perception
so as you know and as
many people at this point might suspect
being a student of D denet I'm no fan of
qualia and phenomenal properties seem to
me you know metaphysically suspect and I
would like to exercise them or at least
deflate them as much as
possible in our ontology
so I think that a lot of problems
related to ineffability and a kind of
intuitions
of phenomenal States being some how
mysterious comes from the fact that in
our perceptual experience for example
let's take Vision as a as a simple
experience a lot of information gets
compounded and compressed in a way where
we are unable to track all the
information that's being you
know uh packed into into a perceptual
representation by our perceptual systems
and so um
so you know you said that so one example
is that colors appear to be intrinsic
properties of objects right to us even
though we know that they are actually
bundles of complex relational properties
that depend not only on the surface
properties of the object but also the
the source of
light uh viewing conditions context our
past experiences uh the state of our
ocular system and also how our visual
system is processing it right so there's
a complex Nexus of conditions that
obtain outside and inside of us that
make colors appear in a certain way H
and yet all this stuff is kind of
flattened into this perception of colors
as properties of objects that are out
there in the world and I think that so
that's part of the story but even if we
if even if I present to you you know the
best
state-of-the-art knowledge about color
perception you will say like yeah but
there's something ineffable missing
there's this
qualitative Gena of of of phenomenal
experience and I think that this is
perhaps because in our
perception there are Pathways for
example to subcortical areas which might
be imbuing our perceptual experience
with as you said some kind of slight
emotional sence right or something like
that so what people have called in the
literature as micro valances right yeah
yeah um so I find this picture
attractive especially I find attractive
the idea that somehow affect might play
a role here but I think that we have
very at this point in time at least we
have very limited uh very limited
evidence for that so this is something
that we're doing now in Brussels trying
to find out more about uh the effective
ladness of of uh perception and also
it's worth
taking into consideration just finally
kind of as a reconciliatory note the
fact that you know even if perceptual
States as such sensory states are
not penetrated or somehow imbued with
effective or other types of information
from other area brain areas or brain
processes that doesn't mean that our
perceptual experiences as a complex
cannot bring all these things together
right
so the perceptual experiences are
extremely complex so it's not just about
sensory properties Drey has for example
written a lot about you know how
Concepts structure our perceptual
experiences so there are sensory
properties in our perceptual experience
but it seems that there's much more
happening yeah than just the sensory
properties alone and that's something
I'm happy to concede and I think is
highly plausible but the claim that you
know I see the the candy bar rapper as
brighter because I'm hungry right that's
I would I would I would be very cautious
about this type of CLA you see that that
that's the kind of paradigmatic example
right because um I think you're
absolutely right we need to bracket off
the domains in which perception might be
from which perception might be influenc
so affect is clearly permeating
perception uh and and clearly uh the
preferences or the PRI or the hypotheses
are affecting that right as you say h
hungriness is a perfect example such
that there is this prediction error or
free energy spiking with respect to this
one homeostatic Prius and that permeates
my experience that becomes a uh you know
a kind of just all
pervasive um yeah uh experience the
other thing that clearly in some the
wrong is the wrong word pervasive but is
over you know intrinsic to my experience
is the attentional modulations the the
rivets and the peaks of my
prioritization and clearly as I say and
I outline this paper preferences are
shaping that um such that I'm hungry the
candy bar is going to draw my attention
I think this is fair enough to say more
than it would when I'm full right like I
had this experience yesterday I went out
for lunch I was really I was with
friends I was really hungry and there
you know news you know news agent shops
or whatever selling food and you're in
that state of hunger
drawn to that and then I leave and I'm
like I don't care I don't want to see it
but yeah exactly the point with me does
that actually alter the fundamental
charact you know uh the the the
qualities of that experience now I think
an interesting contribution to this
question is
psychedelics because yeah there's
something about psychedelics which if we
take a kind of Rebus or alus approach
loosens those
priors at at some level right I'm not
saying the the sort of preference priors
but the priors over let's say um I don't
know like it's kind of like in dreams
right like you might have a prior that
um I can't sort of dissolve through
walls I don't know like this clearly
there's probably no but something like
that and clearly something in like
dreams and psychedelics that gets
loosened such that in perception I seem
in the dream to be able to sort of blend
through walls and and so on now there
there there does seem to be a relaxing
of a mechanistic prior that permits um
changes in my visual experience in this
case I guess the question here is
slightly different is there could there
be changes also in my sort of preference
priors such that if I was uh if I was
super hungry and then took siloc cybin
would would it literally change my
visual of uh perception or is it just
that the mechanistic part of that is
changed so there's kind of two different
priors or preferences that we need to be
talking about as well can you can you
sorry can you repeat the last part so if
you took silos cybin it would change
what because I think that you lost me
there at the at the very end so I guess
what I'm saying is you know the way
people talk about well the Rebus
hypothesis relax on psychedelics is
somewhat vague about which it's a kind
of narrative account of Prior it just
relaxes and I think KL has said this
himself I'm sure Robin would as well but
there are different types of priors so
one would be a kind of mechanistic Prior
okay what do I expect to appear in my
perceptual experience so I do not expect
uh you know two things to be in one
place at the same time I don't expect
for things to move through solid objects
yeah but then there's also the kind of
what you know you could call phenotypic
or preference priors which is defining
of the organism I expect uh to be
satiated I expect my blood glucose level
to be a certain level I expect my
temperature to be a certain level now
seems to me that what siloc cybin is
doing is relaxing those mechanistic
priors such that you can start seeing
things go through walls and the same in
dreams and whatnot but I don't know how
strong the evidence is that it changes
the preference priors right does it it
would so my thought experiment was if I
was really
hungry and then took siloc cybin I can
imagine it would hijack my attentional
apparatus such that I would start homing
in on all the food
but would it literally you know would my
steak start like glistening would my
candy bar start I don't know I guess at
that point it's kind of hard to say what
what part of the system is being altered
but that was kind of the the fault
experiment okay okay I see I see now um
yeah so well it's clear that
psychedelics can induce sythetic
experiences right so so they can
alter how we perceptually experience the
world
dramatically and uh they can make us
experience you know certain uh this kind
of modality
mixing States right so so you you see
the music for example stuff like that so
so that seems to be a very deep uh
change in in how you experience the
world in a sensory way mhm so that's one
thing um I totally agree with you about
the mechanistic priors and the fact that
this seems to happen uh on drugs a
lot um and that there is yeah that that
that that as just as you mentioned as in
dreaming like they seem to be relaxed so
you're entertaining hypothesis that
would otherwise be
outside of of the hypothesis space that
you could entertain and what's also
interesting about dreams and
hallucinations is that at least from a
philosophical perspective that
philosophers often kind of create this
stman idea of hallucinations as
something that's you know you're you're
suddenly in a state where you don't know
that you're hallucinating and you're
confusing hallucination for reality this
is actually extremely rare given given
current evidence and it seems that
people under the influence of
psychedelics very often are aware that
they are
hallucinating just as sometimes people
in undergoing lucid dreaming they can
enter a lucid dream by re realizing kind
of having this moment of aha of oh my
God this is completely unrealistic yeah
um which is in itself also interesting
because that means that you you you're
relaxing a prior on certain levels of
the hierarchy or in certain parts of the
system but at the same time there might
be aspects of the system that are still
kind of monitoring what's going on and
are able to sayy this is this is not
reality this is we're we're on drugs now
right um that's one thing and then
finally going to these preference or
phenotypical priers I think that's an
open question one thing that's for sure
is that and I don't know anything about
the
literature uh that speaks about this
change in these type of Prior in
preference prior
during these psychodelic experiences but
there is a lot of evidence that
psychodelic experiences do change
people's preferences and behaviors long
term right so so there's this famous
effect that people who have
undergone uh a psychedelic experience
are for months afterwards scoring higher
on openness and lower on neuroticism and
and and these kinds of personality
traits which would I would at least
correct if I'm wrong I would ascribe to
a change precisely in these phenotypic
priors where sure you're kind of
changing your behavior or your attitude
towards the world and people yeah uh
because of that experience so perhaps
within the experience it's also possible
now you know whether whether there would
be this permeation of perceptual or
sensory experiences by your preferences
that's a very interesting question and
uh I mean we're in the kind of gold an
age of psychedelic research these days
so I'm sure that sooner or
later someone is going to control the
conditions of their experiment in a way
where they will be able to show that
this happens or it doesn't happen
perhaps right well I guess yeah it's
it's it's super important to unpick
exactly what the hypothesis would be in
that in in in that experiment because as
you say clearly as you yeah I mean
there's overwhelming evidence that of
course you get these longer term effects
and then modulating perception and
conscious experience in interesting ways
but again the question is still there
which is okay what part of your
conscious experience is it uh modulating
so okay you're more open you're less
neurotic it's going to be changing your
attentional schema it's going to be
changing your effective schema right the
things that used to piss you off are
probably going to piss you off a little
bit less you might be less reactive so
you might have more space between the
the percept and the response but is
again I mean I mean the really really
the kind of fundamental question here is
how much of conscious experience is
there beyond all of that you know like
how much is color these kind of
supposedly intrinsic things that are
not um
overlays even though we know
mechanistically they might be overlays
for sure like to what degree do are they
are they just part of all of those
things I mean the evidence kind of the
my intuition is that they're not because
I could pay attention to something but
that doesn't change it it changes the
way that I am living with it right I
same with affect it doesn't change I
mean I don't know it's hard to say you
know no no no no I this is a this is not
so this is not uh an argument that has
not like this argument has been made
before right so this idea that when stay
off intuition when you're paying
attention to something it changes your
quality the quality of your relationship
to that thing yeah it's like with a
camera you know you're looking through a
lens of a camera and you're adjusting
the focus but it doesn't change the
object or the contents of of what you're
seeing right so so so people have argued
against kind of predictive processing
stories that attention might be kind of
uh narrowing the the distribution right
making it more precise but it's not
changing fundamentally what you're
perceiving right it's if it was red it's
still red yeah yeah yeah and
[Music]
um uh yeah and and so because I guess
the thing here is it's not changing what
you're saying I mean again like we kind
of have to distinguish between the numo
and the phenomenal right it's not I mean
I don't think anyone would argue that
it's like unless you think that you know
you have some quantum mechanics and you
think there's Observer like Park calling
of that and you Tony the mechanics of
course if I look at my computer I'm not
it's not sudden apart from the very sort
of potential Photon changes I'm not
morphing it into something that it
wasn't sure but phenomenally the as you
say the contents of my
experience I don't know I'm a little I'm
a little L I'm a little less secure on
that front um I mean I'm just noticing
things that I didn't notice
before which in a sense is changing the
content but whether it's changing the
content as it pertains to the object
itself is a slightly different question
right so for example uh the yeah so so
one way to think about it is so so okay
so we have to kind of I think separate
several things yeah so one thing is that
uh my claim and the claim you know that
other that that Joe has made together
with me in the in our paper is
that
um attention is kind of modulated is is
is corresponding to what what block
labels Act Consciousness right so so so
attention is not supposed to give you a
full account of phenomenal qualities
that's that's one
thing um and I think most people most
higher order theorist theorists agree
with this that you know you can probably
do more than you expect with just this
kind of story about introspection or
some kind of higher order lower order
relationship so people tend to think
that you cannot get any quality postive
information there that's not entirely
true uh and
um uh Andy Clark has actually a very
good paper I think from 2000 or 2003
called access
implies uh access implies quality I
don't remember the title now I'll find
it uh it's a very nice paper is it a
case where access implies qualia yes
that's 2000 yeah uh yeah so that's a
nice paper also that
shows that the distinction between axis
and phenomenal Consciousness might not
be as clear-cut as block and his
supporters would like but just to be
clear on our picture attention is just
you know this kind of probing mechanism
in the netian terms it's it's this
access to information mechanism yeah and
now so that's one thing uh now the
second thing is as you said that um that
the the claim about whether it changes
the content drastically whether paying
attention to something changes the
content of your experience and here
again we have to be very careful because
something can
change
uh your experience can change in some
qualitative ways without the content
changing per se so so Drey has this very
nice example where
he Compares two situations one in which
I show you a piece of paper on which I
drew 30 dots and I you know I just kind
of show it to you like this it off and
then in another case I show you the same
piece of paper but there are 31 dots so
technically speaking technically
speaking the number of dots has changed
between the two pictures so the content
of your experience has changed Technic
at least that's the point that he would
like to make in my in my view unless you
notice that there's an extra dot the
content of your experience has not
changed right and it's only through
sharpening of attention Could you
actually notice that there was a
difference right in your in the between
the between the two percepts so so so I
think that there are these cases where
indeed uh paying attention can change
the quality of your experience even
though it might not change explicitly
the contents of your experience
interesting that's an division right
because I think most would view those as
isomorphic they would view contents of
experience and for and the phenomenal
qualities of experience as isomorphic
yes so so I think it's useful to maybe
think of oops I think I'm getting now
sun is shine into the
office uh so so you might think about
this in terms of modes of presentation
of content right so attention seems to
attention is not only picking out what
aware of but it can change the mode of
presentation of what you're aware of to
some extent just as I said earlier with
the metaphor of sharpening the the the
focus on the camera lens yeah the the
the subject in the picture doesn't
change but what's changes is kind of the
way you're capturing the picture with
your camera and I think this is this
this might this kind of talk of modes of
presentation might be useful as a as a
useful kind of intermediate step between
the the content itself so what is
represented yeah the way it's
represented right um this mode of
presentation those that that distinction
might be might be useful here as well do
you think there's a strict do you think
one can draw a strict line there between
contents and mode is that do you think
that's feasible I mean is there a kind
of taxonomy of modes in which things can
be uh perceived or can my mode in some
ways become opaque and become a content
I think the latter can probably happen
so so I there's there's not many people
in philosophy of Mind these days talking
about M of presentation so charers is
what is I guess the the main figure when
it comes to that uh Hilla Jacobson talks
actually about something similar when it
comes to effective uh effective coloring
of
perception
um and uh some other people do as well
but it's a very small group of people
these days that talk about modes of
presentation as distinct from contents
but I definitely think that there is a
there is a there there are cases where
we conflate the the way we experience
things or the way they are presented to
us in experience with what they are so I
think I think so hila Jacobson has for
example a very
nice uh example that she uses in her
paper as part of her argument which is
that the same object the same food item
can look delicious
and disgusting to two people yeah and so
what seems to they they are looking at
the same thing right so so the sensory
properties do not change presumably or
we can even assume that the sensory
properties don't change between their
two
experiences but the effective mode of
presentation of these two sensory
experiences can be dramatically
different right so so and and a simple
example that I used in my talks
of hijacking Hill's argument is is a
piece of licorice because people often
think that you know people can have
strong reactions to different food items
and licorice is a is a piece of sweet
that almost or Marmite would be another
example those are two things that people
have very very strong opinions about and
they have very strong reactions to but
the a jar of Marmite or a stick of
licorice are not by themselves repulsive
to us people just perceive them as
disgusting or delicious and you know
they can have this kind of different
ways of engaging with that content so
maybe that's another way of thinking
about mode of presentation as as this
kind of way in which you engage with the
with the content of your experience
right what's uh Shakespeare there's
nothing good or bad but only thinking
makes it
so yeah yeah that's that's Hamlet um yes
I mean Shakespeare I guess wasn't
thinking about whether yeah I guess uh I
would have of course I have no issue
with the idea that licorice might
look words Fair here might look
disgusting or look attractive to people
but I guess the question is do they look
disgusting and look attractive to people
are we overlaying that or is it
suffusing our I mean even if it's not
overlaying it might be suffusing our
experience the question there as we were
talking about is are the sensory
properties being altered but I guess I
mean I guess that's a I guess it's an
experimental question ultim I mean how
you could how you could do that without
qualitative report I mean that that
which might be quite limited I'm not
sure because again I mean language fails
us here so this is what we're interested
in here in Brussels right now and and
one way you could think about it is well
do you see
changes uh in the sensory processing
areas right when you're when you're
putting people in a brain scan right do
you see changes in activity depending on
the veilance of the stimulus that
they're showing them so so a common
stimulus used in experiments on uh
affect are smiling and unhappy or
frowning faces or or angry faces right
so you show them two types of faces they
distinguish whether they are happy or
not and then the question is where do
you see the difference between
the happy and the and the frowning faces
right is the is the difference
represented the difference represented
in
some area of the brain that's associated
for example with processing value yeah
uh some kind of one of the frontal areas
or is it maybe or whether we can find
the differences already on the level of
perceptual processing so this is
something that we're aiming
to uh to test here and there is there's
kind of the the
available uh evidence is kind of
equivocal I would say so there are some
papers that show differences in
perceptual areas there is also some work
that's been done in Nicholas krias
scores lab which seems to show that
there are
actually it's not that the differences
are represented in sensory modalities
but there is a sensory modality specific
coding for the veilance of the stimulus
so you could think that there's a
universal code for Value in the
brain but in order to compare where you
have to bring two different stimuli
right so if I if I ask you if I show you
a happy face and a monetary reward
something like that if I give you two
two different types of stimuli if you're
comparing if you have to do some kind of
a trading off between them um you have
to bring them into some kind of a common
neural
currency yeah so there's K ctis lab uh
has shown that there might be this
Universal value coding but before items
are brought into this Universal value
coding for comparison there's also a a
modality specific coding of value uh in
the brain that is not sensory per se but
there is there are differences in how
values are
coded uh depending on the modality from
which the information comes which would
seem to be this kind of intermediate
state where your perceptual experience
might
be uh effectively Laden even if the
sensory properties stay the same because
what's there's something that's being
added you know on top of sensory
properties it's not changing how the Hue
and the brightness and the color that
you're perceiving but that there's
something else that's overlaid on that
as you suggested earlier that is
changing the character of the overall
perceptual experience and this is
precisely Hilla Jacobson's View and also
Frederic de Vino has a recent paper
where she also adopts a view like that
so much to read so much to read I'm
writing down notes I mean yeah I mean
I'm very impressed I mean it's funny
that we still haven't resolved these
issues uh since 1983 when Jerry Fodor
wrote modularity of the mind I me he he
he would if he was still here he would
have loved to um he would have loved to
have uh listened to this conversation
because I'm sure he'd have lots of
opinions but perhaps or he would be
maybe he would love to or maybe he would
be extremely frustrated you
know yeah well I'm sure I'm sure again I
did I never met Jerry of course but I'm
sure he would uh whatever it was I heard
he was very he was an opinionated man I
mean for good for good or for bad okay
cool um that was that was that was super
interesting I mean I love that I read
modularity than M when I was at Uni and
loved it I mean I loved it as an
intellectual Endeavor I mean I had no
skin in the game but um I thought it was
I thought
I also think there's a lot you can learn
about writing clearly and
precisely from from foder and from Drey
so I've never read any Drey I mean he's
come up over and over again I had a
little foray into I read one of the like
radical and activist books
um okay can't remember who wrote it and
there's a lot of sort of dryan and
milikan sort of critiques as in they're
critiquing them because they don't think
that any you know only represent the
only representations are those which are
socially scaffolded yeah oh so it's the
second book by uh
Dan May yeah and Eric mine yeah the the
basic Minds evolved I think yeah I read
I read yeah I read one of them um and
again like it's not really my argument
um but it was interesting enough I
should read milikin and and dry but life
is life is short high but they're highly
recommended so so I really
um knowledge and the flow of information
especially if you're working on
predictive processing and these topics I
think it's a really beautiful book that
probably is the first philosophy of Mind
book that took information Theory
seriously uh even though there are some
distortions and he at some point
develops his own kind of you know
version of of of Shannon's communication
Theory kind of Mong view in the end but
but it's a beautiful book and it's an
extremely funny fact that that book was
published in 81 I think
so 30 something years after you know
Shannon's commun mathematical theory of
communication became a thing and this
kind of shows you how long it sometimes
takes for philosophers to you know catch
wind of what's happening in science did
um this is a kind of historical question
did Chomsky ever reference Shannon was
try do you know if trky was aware of
Shannon
I'm I think it would be strange if he
wasn't given that he was you know where
he was working and that would be
surprising to me however I don't
actually know so so I've read
Chomsky uh but a long time ago like his
linguistic writings a long time ago and
I mostly the last things I've read were
mostly about
um about mental representations oh
really yeah so so he has a very very
deflationist view of mental
representations you can probably find
him you can ALS Francis Egan in some of
her papers okay takes his minimal view
of what she calls erat's
representationalism as a kind of uh
Target yeah I did uh I did Linguistics
as my undergrad oh okay so I I read
Chomsky from you know um syntactic
structures all the way to minimalism uh
but this was all very sort of biological
Linguistics about in you know the
question of whether Linguistics there
you know a lad an innate linguistic
device or things like this so slightly
different but uh yeah I was just
wondering because obviously he was
writing in you know the 60s 70s so yeah
yeah okay uh on the question of
representations I mean actually it's
funny because both people I've had on
who are expert in representations you
and Alex kefir have both recommended me
dry and I'm Alex's work on
representation is great so I am a of his
work you I really liked your uh moderate
predictive processing paper it was
challenging because um I feel I it kind
of made me realize like oh I've been
taking the vanilla predictive processing
because I'm not personally in my own
writing I'm not wedded to any particular
architecture whether it's discrete State
space continuous State space I take the
vanilla position I run with it and so on
but it made me think like oh there's so
much more for me to learn exactly about
predictive coding predictive processing
schema well I found really interesting
was this idea of well this ambiguity
more broadly in the literature about
what is being represented at different
layers of the predicted processing
hierarchy so you say and can quote um
there's an ambiguity between levels
which perform the function of standing
in for features of the
environment uh and those which act only
as meta representations by standing in
for the features of levels
Downstream so there's this idea that
obviously the high you know the higher
you the higher layers are predicting I
mean all layers are predicting but you
know they're predicting the layer
beneath them and the prediction area is
rising up and there's kind of this
meeting in the middle and this Hier this
horizontal explaining way of prediction
error but I thought you this is a really
nice observation which is where does the
external world come in right because
there seems to be this equivocation
where we say okay we're predicting the
external States across the mark of
blanket but then in this predicted
processing scheme we're actually only
predicting the ne the layer below and so
there might only be one layer which is
actually receiving the sensory input so
where where have your where you know
this was 2017 you wrote this paper where
have your thoughts now evolv to with
respect to the architecture of
predictive
processing uh yeah so just on that quote
right so so just to be clear about what
I was kind of attacking there so so what
I was attacking is this ambiguity
between in in an in how people answer
the question about what is the function
of of a layer in a in a predictive
coding hierarchy so is it representing
the world as some people will say or is
it predicting what's happening just
below on the level below and a lot of
people when I first encountered
predictive coding and uh it was very
informed by Mark SPAC who was my master
thesis supervisor in edinb and he the
way he presented it to us initially
was uh in saying that the brain is just
minimizing the the story is that the
brain is minimizing prediction errors
and that's all it cares about and then
it turns out that the best way to
minimize prediction errors is actually
to represent the world right so so so to
kind
of have the the the brain become a kind
of distorted of course but a mirror of
nature in some ways and that this is
this the reason why predictive
processing offers a a kind of a story
about the organism building up its own
model model of the world is because by
building the the the process of building
up your own model of the world is just
the best strategy for long-term
prediction error
minimization um and so my problem in
that paper was that different people
want to clink to different
interpretations of what a single layer
in the hierarchy is doing depending on
what on what serves their
wider uh wider philosophical Pro object
so people who are
anti-representationalist will say like
oh you know the function of a layer is
just to predict what's happening on the
layer below uh and other people will say
like the function of a layer is to
represent the regularities in the
environment at a certain level of
abstraction and at a c in a certain time
uh
window and both of these interpretations
can be true according to predictive
processing it's just that which one
you're try you're emphasizing seems to
depend on your uh external let's call
them or at least external to the
framework philosophical assumptions and
convictions and this is why when I wrote
that paper it was already becoming
apparent that for example
Carl uh is uable to different
interpretations of predictive processing
or predictive coding or active inference
whatever you want to call it depending
on who he's coauthoring a paper with so
so if he's coauthoring with an an
activist he will take a more an activist
stance where he will uh try to avoid
talking about internal representations
or or the or building up an internal
model of the environment yeah when he's
writing with someone who's uh coming
from a more cognitivist fodorian
uh persu with with a kind of fodorian
persuasion then he will lean more into
the representational
talk so it seems that uh that there was
this
ambiguity uh about what's what's
happening in the framework
and today I think I'm kind
of
um so I used to think that maybe there's
a definite answer to this question which
interpretation is correct today I'm
actually thinking that uh the semantics
maybe are kind
of disconnected from the from the formal
layer MH so I have this I I'm I'm at
least when it comes to predictive
processing I think there is no
definitive answer whether we should
think of the generative models for
example as representations or not I
think that this will depend on your
other commitments about what a
representation is for
example uh on the wider goal of what
explanatory project you're engaging in I
think those are the things that will
actually determine which inter
interpretation you will apply to
predictive processing but I'm not uh
really committed to to either of the
interpretations and
um this goes a little bit back to
attention in the sense that I think what
you attending to in the predictive
processing story might influence how you
will want to
interpret uh the framework I'm sorry if
this is kind of a oh no I love it not
satisfying answer you know it's maybe
I'm the same I'm the same uh despite
being a host and and I feel like part of
being a host of active inference podcast
is in some ways you should be wedded to
certain ideas I'm pretty ambivalent
about or not even ambivalent I'm open
right I'm epistemically open I don't
know um that might frustrate some people
but I don't know uh and also this isn't
really I don't really have an area of
expertise yet so so I appreciate the I
appreciate the epistemic humility I mean
it's an open qu I mean I mean
fundamentally one of the issues is no
one really knows what representations
are I mean like what what what the I
mean as you say all philosophical the
all theories have their miracles they
have their axom right so are you a dreki
and are you a milikan follower are you
you know do you think that there needs
to be a you know a strict isomorphism
between that which is representing and
that which is represented and so on and
so forth I wondering whether even if we
park the sort of what is being predicted
whether it's the lir below or whether
it's the world
what are the sort of unifying features
therefore that we've come to in terms of
a predicted processing landscape so for
example there's this idea that the
priors of one level are the posterior
furnished from the lay above yeah now
what does that really mean is that is
that what the is that what people talk
about when they're talking about
predictions coming down the
hierarchy and and I guess the question
here is and I said this to Alex as well
I think there's a real I mean I struggle
visually conceptually to really imagine
a predictive processing hierarchy
because I always view it as in time
right dynamically uning such that you
have these I mean at a very vanilla
level fine prediction eras coming up
predictions coming down and they get
canceled at some point you get a
hypothesis woo the world appears like
great but when you actually start
thinking about okay mathematically
formally what are the architectures that
we're setting up in place it becomes
very tricky for me to imagine because I
think of a layer that is simultaneously
predicting and being predicted and
explaining away prediction error so just
at a very broad level is there for
myself and for other people listening
and watching a way of like formally
disambiguating what might be happening
or should we just say this is some
dynamic system and you can kind of get
by with the vanilla approach I think
you're putting me in a position where
which is you know way above my pay grade
here
no but
um uh yeah that paper you that paper you
do cover quite a lot of technical
round a little bit but I must say that
also I'm not entirely sure how well you
know my technical
grasp has so so whether I was that
correct there when about in the things
that I was writing did anyone send you
an angry email no no never never but
this this I I'll answer that question
your question first and then I'll tell
you one anecdote about this paper
um
so um so yeah so you're right that
there's a lot of variability when it
comes to how you can
implement the general predictive coding
scheme and uh Michael spratling has a
very nice paper from 2007 called an
overview of predictive coding
algorithms where he Compares different
first of all he gives a kind of a brief
historical overview of linear predictive
coding and where it came from and then
he talks about the three uh yeah the
three major varieties of predictive
coding as applied to hierarchical
networks which is ran Bard's original
model uh Carl's uh free energy
minimization model and his own
predictive coding through biased
division modulation I believe that's his
the name of his algorithm so he Compares
these three algorithms and Michael
spraing is
a is actually a guy from London who who
has done uh a lot of work on modeling uh
neural populations using predictive
coding and building very large neural
networks performing different cognitive
tasks by through by implementing
implementing predictive coding and so uh
one of the problems that that paper
highlights is that because there are
many different ways of doing predictive
coding you know it's not stable from one
algorithm to another what the prediction
error is right and you know what is
propagated upwards what what is
propagated
downwards even how to delineate a layer
of the hierarchy well quite yeah uh so
so there's a lot of and that's what I
also touch uh that's what I also touch
on in
that 2017 paper moderate predictive
processing so there seems to be a number
of possible ways of doing predictive
coding and depending which model you
will or algorithm rather I should say
you'll pick there will be certain
differences and what counts as what so
in the end when I was writing my PhD I
actually decided to go to a higher level
of abstraction
and I looked at the work of Iris vanroy
and Johan kout from radbot University in
Nan in the Netherlands so they have a
bunch of papers in which they formalize
predictive
coding on a more course grained in a
more course grained way as
uh by using basically basian graphs and
imagining each layer of the hierarchy as
a basian graph with certain dependencies
and uh you know connections between
variables so in their model they assume
that each layer of the hierarchy very
much like in fistance models each layer
of the hierarchy which will have a set
of hidden
variables and a set of prediction
variables right and these uh these these
variables will correspond to uh yeah so
so these two types of variables will
correspond to kind of the the latent
variables and the so-called observed
variables in a way where the the latent
variables are the are the hidden
variables that get inputs from The
observed variables on the level above
when predictions are gener predictions
are
generated uh and this will be integrated
and then at the same time will'll issue
predictions so so will influence the
state of their their own observ observed
variables and these will kind of cascade
downstairs so so they imagine this kind
of simple probabilistic graphs that are
connected uh one to another and they
kind of operate in this kind of two
stages right so they either do inference
or they or they um observe what's
happening and I think that's a very uh
General this is probably the most
General way in which you can think of
predictive coding or addictive
processing because it leaves out error
units so they don't talk about how
errors are propagated into the system
where the where the errors should be
connected to to things and stuff like
that and that's I think really an
important abstraction
because the way errors are processed are
dramatically different between different
predictive coding
algorithms and their very abstract and
very general way of for normalizing
predictive coding has the one crucial
benefit that it abstracts away from
different algorithms so that you could
still capture the general similarities
between these algorithms without talking
you know or getting bogged down from my
perspective into the minutia of how each
of the algorithms is implemented exactly
now there's a trade of in going via that
route because by going for a higher
level of abstraction you're of course
losing detail and if you're losing
detail sometimes you might actually find
out that you cannot disambiguate certain
claims about predictive coding on that
higher level of abstraction so people
who have for example very demanding
views of mental representations as
structural representations that are
capable of action guidance and error
correction and stand in some kind of
homomorphic relationship to their
targets in the environment well it
becomes very difficult to disambiguate
whether
these abstractly captured predictive
coding layers are working as structural
representations because you've left out
so much detail on the table that you're
just not able to exactly adjudicate
whether they fulfill all the criteria or
not right so so the fact that an
abstract abstracted and idealized
description doesn't fulfill these
criteria that these people will have for
mental representation doesn't mean that
a particular model like spread
links Network or fistance network
wouldn't fulfill these
criteria uh on its own when it's
properly implemented with with a greater
uh level of
detail that's again not a very
satisfying answer I feel no look I no I
mean I'm glad personally that it other
people find it confusing
and that I can go to spratling or Carl
what remind me of the two Netherlands
the two Dutch people who you were
influenced by Iris Iris vanroy Iris Iris
the way you would write it in
English van and Roy is rou i j yeah and
Johan
kout okay perfect thank you so highly
recommended uh very good
very good Visions no that this is I like
because I I think part of um part of my
role here is to point people in certain
directions right um so I'm seeing here
cognitive cognition and
intractability so they they they they
worked a lot on cognition and
intractability I think um the paper I'm
thinking of or the where the
formalization appears is something like
to be precise the details don't matter
oh there's free energy minimization and
information G the devil is in the
details might be that yeah that's I
think a commentary on Carl's paper where
he mixes discreet and continuous
variables so I'm thinking of uh 2017
Johan kout Harold beckering and Iris
vanroy to be precise the details don't
matter unpredictive processing precision
and level of detail of
predictions that's in brain and
cognition okay fantastic well thank you
for that uh it's a paper that definitely
influenced a lot of my thinking about uh
about attention in the in the excellent
I mean it's a sh framewor it's a shame I
wrote this paper before um it's
difficult to keep up with all the
literature because also the literature
has ballooned so I started my PhD in
2014 and at some point I was just
getting like there were 20 papers coming
every month on the topics that I was
working on just from people working on
predictive processing so you know there
were in five months I had a 100 papers
to read which is kind of yeah yeah
unmanageable right so so so um some
point that literature just exploded I'd
like to know your anecdote about this so
so the anecdote since this is you know a
public facing podcast or at least I hope
hopefully the the academically facing
podcast
the the story about this paper is that I
wrote it uh I guess it came out in 2017
It Was Written somewhere between Yeah
March 2017 it came out so it was written
mostly in 2016 so the early days of my
uh PhD in fact and
um and it was a little bit you know it
was hot on the heels of Andy Clark's
radical predictive processing which is
which the title is supposed to be a
reference to and the debate between
radical and conservative predictive
processing so precisely
this
uh representation light or
representation heavy interpretations of
predictive processing and I made a
terrible mistake when naming this paper
because it's called moderate predictive
processing and to me at the time it was
very clear what the title refers to and
what it is about yeah um and I thought
you know it appeared in this collection
of papers philosophical papers on
predictive processing edited by Thomas
metzinger and Vana visa and so I thought
like everyone will know like this will
be obvious that if you're reading like
if you're Googling stuff about mental
representation and predictive processing
people will just find this paper no
problem and it actually turned out that
because the title wasn't immediately
informative people just didn't know what
this paper is about
so I was meeting people in you know four
years later or three years later who had
no idea that like this paper came out
and they were I was sitting in talks and
people were talking to me
about the these things and they had no
idea that this paper came out and at the
time it was one of the very few papers
about mental representation and
predictive processing but because it was
just badly named just people it didn't
show up in searches so I would advise
and I would advise I would advise
especially Junior people to to be
mindful of how you title your work yes
because that actually can change the
discoverability of your work quite
significantly yeah they prob they
thought you were making a political
point they thought you
were H very good yeah no you're
absolutely right just like fill the
title with buzzword right just free
energy free make sure the word free
energy in there or active inference um
yeah just yeah well discussing public
facing work people are going to be
surprised if I don't mention the
emperor's new mark of blankets but I
don't want to spend too much time we've
been going for a while as well and I'm
aware youve probably got dinner I've got
dinner and so on but it's sort of your I
mean again this is not this was not your
solo project um this was actually I
don't know whether did jelly brunenberg
lead this or was his name just first up
uh so the way that project came about is
because y came to bom where I was at the
time just fresh after my PhD and he gave
a talk about Mark of
blankets uh which is also by the way a
topic which placed prominently in the
previous paper we discussed in the 2017
paper about mental representations where
I talk about the insulation of the mark
of blank with a mark of blanket between
different layers of the hierarchy so
after my after my after I finished my
PhD y came to B and he gave a talk with
his where he was just trying to
understand the difference between Mark
of blankets as they're described in the
literature on probabilistic modeling and
and in literature on basian inference
and how they are used and described in
free energy modeling and so he was very
confused uh I was very confused and so
that was a paper that he was that was a
talk which where he credited it
to Manuel baltieri and himself that was
something that that was a project that
they were discussing and working on he
gave the talk and I later told him like
y I love this project because I've been
trying to figure out how they understand
Mark of blankets for a while now and it
was something that I kind of bumped into
during my PhD and I it wasn't entirely
clear what is the correspondence between
the way that friston describes Mark of
blanket and and how Pearl describes Mar
of Blancas during my PhD I bought
Pearl's uh 1990 book I believe u on
probabilistic inference in thinking
machines I don't remember the whole
title but it's the book in which he
which is often credited as the source in
which he introduced the notion of a mark
of blanket so I bought the book I read
the whole book and I still didn't
understand how it's supposed to gel with
the free energy stuff and then for half
a year or something like that you
know I was like okay Y and Manuel wrote
the paper it's all good I I I don't know
half a year more probably passed and and
I talked to I was talking to Joe and we
were talking about something completely
unrelated a paper that Joe was writing
at the time which also had some
probabilistic modeling elements in it
and we talked again about Mark of
blankets because we were talking about
this topic and
uh I said hey I got a great reference
for you because I'm I'm I wanted to
write something about this but Y and
Manuel I think already wrote a paper
about this so I'm going to ask y if he
has a draft and I'll send it to you and
so I contacted Y and it turned out that
they haven't written the paper that the
paper kind of you know they they they
didn't have the time to to figure
everything out it kind of laid in the in
the in the in a that was locked in a
closet so to speak where it was kind of
Sitting Waiting for a better time and uh
and somehow we just proposed that hey
maybe we could collaborate on this maybe
we could help you bring the paper back
so we discussed this stuff and
uh uh we started writing a paper then we
started thinking okay so where should we
where should we try to pitch this paper
like what Journal are we writing for and
I think it might have been me although
I'm not entirely sure who said you know
hey how about BBS like because it's it's
it's it's getting a little bit annoying
these people in the free energy
literature they're stting they're
starting to claim that a bacterium has a
mark of blanket a brain has a mark of
blanket a person has a mark of blanket
the Earth has a mark of blanket right
there are all these papers about the
biosphere or the climate as a mark of
planetary Mark of blanket and so maybe
given how important and how prominent
Carl's work in computational
neurosciences these days maybe we can
pit it to BBS and so we wrote a whole
draft we we we we sent it to BBS and the
rest is kind of History so we had yeah
so okay eight reviewers I can tell you
about that yeah that that that is crazy
I've had
three well that's a lot eight is I mean
obviously that's my I haven't got
anything out yet so these are all in
process three is three felt like a lot
eight is outrageous um well the good
thing is that the more reviewers you
have the kind of the more of a Arena it
becomes where you can try to pitch them
against each other in your responses
right so you can and and we did have in
in our reviews we did get you know
reviews where One reviewer
said cut this out this is irrelevant and
the other reviewer said oh I find this
bit really nice I'm really happy that
it's there so right well okay so I mean
this this paper I mean this I feel like
when I read this paper I view it in
concert with um The Mark of blanket
trick so I I view those the these as
kind of coupled uh critiques of active
inference or predictive processing
critiques I actually think is H it
probably is a critique um I actually I
read these as more like specul they're
not speculative in a derogatory way but
they're calling into question right
they're saying okay let's let's get
clearer on the terms that using so for
example a distinction that you draw here
is between a so-called marov blanket and
a friston blanket precisely what what
just in sort of layman's terms without
getting into you know the granularities
of Pearl and I'm going to ask who did
the math in that paper because I'm kind
of amazed you know I looked at the list
because sometimes you see there's like
five philosophers and a mathematician
and you know they've done all the
formula formula and I was like oh no
there's four philosophers here I'm like
this is really cool that they've also
done this um without like getting into
the granularities of the variables what
is the difference between a friston
blanket and a mark of blanket like in
short yeah okay so in very short terms
without uh going into the details of you
know Pear's work so so the main idea in
graphical models is that sorry in basian
graphical models I should say Invasion
directed graphical models is that you
have a number of variables that are
related by some dependency probabilistic
dependency relations and that's usually
expressed by there being kind of arrows
between the between the variables right
so you have variables that influence
other variables and then if a variable
is dependent probabilistically dependent
on another variable there be there will
be an arrow that connects them pointing
kind of the in the direction in which
the influence go so if there's you know
variable a up here that's modulating the
behavior of variable B down here there
will be an arrow pointing to to from
from one variable to another and that
will mean if there's an arrow connecting
the two variables it will mean that the
dependent variable is conditionally
sorry I shouldn't say conditionally but
it's dependent on the on the on the
variable which is influencing it and so
a mark of blanket in very simple terms
is that if you have a graph structure
where there are different variables
connected and dependent to each other in
different ways uh a mark of blanket
identifies a set of variables which
render some variable of interest a
variable that in which the state of
which we're interested in it renders
that variable of interest conditionally
independent from other variables in the
model so basically it's a set of
variables uh that render the variable of
interest conditionally in the dependent
from the rest of the model so what that
means practically is that you have some
variable that you're investigating and
you're interested in learning everything
you can about that variable that means
that all you have to know about the rest
of the system are the states of the
variables in its Mark of blanket and
that because that Mark of blanket is
kind of shielding that variable from the
rest of the system so if you know the
states of the mark of blanket variables
you know everything there is to to that
is needed to make an inference about the
variable of inference and that's
basically all that Mark of blankets are
right so Mark of blankets are
basically uh a way to
partition the variables in a
directed graphical model probabilistic
graphical model um partition them in a
way where you will be able to effect
efficiently and effectively do inference
about some variable in that model
um and
so what's important about this is that
the the the original formulation of a
mark of blanket by Pearl that doesn't
ascribe any kind of special
relationships there or special functions
to the to the to the variables in the
mark of blanket I mean I maybe yeah like
all of all of the V all of the variables
in the mark of blanket they can be
connected in different ways of course
probabilistic to the variable of
interest but they don't you know none of
them are kind of more important than the
others so to speak um and they don't
play you you cannot learn anything about
the functions they play in the model
just from their positioning in the in
the mark of blank and now here's where
the innovation of Carl friston comes in
which is that Carl friston has
partitioned the variables in the in the
Mark of
blanket into the into so first of all he
partitions them in in two ways so he
calls them the internal variable right
uh and the external variables so so he
assumes that there's the mark of blanket
is kind of separating or shielding the
internal variable which will used to be
our variable of interest in pearls terms
from the rest of the system which is
external to the blanket so to
speak and now the mark of the the second
Innovation is that apart from talking
about internal and external variables he
also starts talking about
uh
uh ER he starts to talk about sorry and
now I have to actually refresh my memory
because this been a while since we wrote
that paper I assum the sensory and
active St yeah exactly I was just
wondering what is exactly the term so
not sensory act sensory States and
active States right so there are the the
states in the so variables in the the
mark of blanket itself can take a kind
of a sensory function or they can take
an active function and the difference
between these two is that some states
some variables in the in the mark of
blanket will take information from
outside of the blanket and these will be
the sensory States and there are some uh
variables in the mark of blanket can
influence what's happening outside of
the blanket so they have kind of these
istic arrows in the model coming out
from from the from the blanket and
influencing external States and these
will be active States
MH uh and this is this this is it seems
at first as a kind of a innocuous you
know distinction yeah sure so so what
you're telling me you could say so you
what you just told me is that like what
Carl noticed is that some variables in
the blanket are influenced by external
variable and some variables in the
blanket are influencing the external
variables right and that would be all
fine good if uh it wasn't that this
distinct this partitioning into active
and sensory and internal external wasn't
pay playing an important role in in
active inference in that it is taken to
delineate a minimal active inference
agent and this is kind of the leap from
from Del from from uh calculating or
delineating a blanket and going into it
giving it an interpret interpretation of
an agent that has some internal States
and is interacting with the external
environment via its perceptual and
active states that that move from one to
another is actually a huge leap because
in Pearl's original formulation of Mark
of blankets you can specify a mark of
blanket for any variable in your
probabilistic directed a cyclical graph
so as long you every variable in the
model will have its own Mark of blanket
and these will be partially overlapping
of course in terms of the variables that
make up the blanket but what's important
is that no variable is kind of
privileged in relationship to the other
variables in the model in terms of uh
it's it's how it's treated so so every
variable has you know a mark of blanket
is just a way for Pearl it's a formal
tool for learning something about the
dependencies in the model nothing more
and now and doing inference of course
over the states of Interest so it's kind
of just a tool that's deployed in a
purely pragmatic way and in fistance
interpretation it becomes something more
because suddenly there's this whole
layer interpretive layer that's added to
the mark of blanket
formalism which implies that you know
variables of Interest are somehow and
Mar and blankets are constitutive of
agents and it seems to and then implies
that you know there are these agents and
and the way that friston uh often kind
of formulates his models there's an
agent that's interacting with the
environment and so the the the the
interpretation of the mark of blanket
under the free energy principle and in
free energy models doesn't seem to be uh
doesn't seem to be
uh sorry seems to
privilege a certain you know certain way
of looking at what the model is supposed
to be doing so it's kind of a built-in
assumption that we're modeling an agent
and this agent is doing something right
in our case minimizing free energy right
yeah yeah yeah so yeah this is this is
interesting this is a conversation
that's come up a lot in this podcast I
wonder whether as a result of papers
like yours um as well as a mark of
blanket trick as well as Mel andrews's
paper vanz other I wonder whether
there's been a general attitude shift
towards a well at least a recognition of
this issue so I I've read the the the
response as well and the commentary to
the responses and you draw a distinction
I think this is interesting between
literalism
realism and let me just check I don't
instrumentalism realism and literalism
and I like there's a graph I I don't
know maybe it's just because I like
graphs there's a nice graph where you
sort of put everyone on the Spectrum um
indeed where what can you in brief I
mean I'm sure people okay so like
instrumentalism I'm sure in part you
know in short we can say okay the of
blanket is a tool for us scientists uh
but it's not actually making any claim
to ontologically say what's going on in
the world and then realism or sorry
literalism would be well no the mark of
blanket literally is a partition in the
physical world what is the addition of
realism there so that's a kind of the
the Spectrum and then you got realism in
the Middle where how does realism carve
up that
space well so I guess uh
the the way I would think about realism
is that
um that
uh that they they identify so so the
realism would be kind of a position
intermediate position where where you
say well there are cases where in which
Mark of
blankets do align with or are can be
used to identify real features of the
world right so so are are set to
identify boundaries in the world uh the
difference to literalism is that in this
interpretation a mark of blanket is
still a tool kind of a a a a way to to
use a way to capture a real difference
in the in the world right uh but you
cannot you someone who's a realist at
least in my understanding and maybe my
coauthors would have a different
understanding also time has passed so we
opinions but my understanding here would
be that literalism is this type of claim
that at some point appeared in the
literature that you know an organism has
a mark of blanket and I think that if
you say an organism has a mark of
blanket you're committing a kind of
category mistake yeah because Mark of
blankets are properties of are formal
properties of models MH
uh and not of
organisms and so a more moderate
position from that is to say well
there's a boundary there's a real
boundary in the world and we can
delineate that boundary using represent
that boundary using a mark of blanket
right yeah and that under some
conditions and like this is really
important because I think we got a lot
of push back for that so we we don't we
never kind of argued against The View
that you can create a model system where
under some
conditions there will be boundaries in
this emergent boundaries in the behavior
of the system such that you can model
these boundaries with Mark of blankets
effic effectively and I think this would
be a kind of a realist position what we
kind of argued against is that some
people have claimed in the literature
before we wrote that paper
that the all this talk about agents uh
having boundaries separating them from
the environment and having internal
external States and so on all this talk
Falls naturally from the math from the
math of probabilistic inference and
variational free energy minimization and
what we wanted to show is that that's
not actually true if it falls from
something it falls from some extra
assumptions that you bring into the
picture it wasn't you know it's it's a
it's a it's a result of assumptions that
you build into your models sometimes and
that's fine if you if you're transparent
about that there's no problem with that
but it's not that you know you just have
a a system where you can delineate a
probabilistic graph you you can
partition the variables and suddenly you
show that oh my God there's an agent in
there right that's that's not it just
doesn't follow in this straight way and
so I think this would be the the clear
difference here between instrument alism
also in literalism where instrumentalism
is you know just being as non-committal
as possible saying we're just doing
modeling we're not claiming that what
we're modeling needs to correspond in
any uh in any truth preserving way to
what's out and there in the world then
there's realism where we say we are
doing modeling but we do claim that
we're tracking something real in the
environment using this formalism and
then literalism is
saying the model is what is being
modeled right the medium is the message
so to so to speak so so the blanket Mark
of blankets are something that organisms
have that are boundaries in the world
that we can talk about boundaries in the
world as Mark of blankets being out
there and that's just nonsense in my
opinion at least so okay okay so yeah so
this is the point right is it that's the
last point that that last point I think
is the really critical one
uh why is it
nonsense that a coupled agent Arena
relationship has a mark of blanket like
what what is the part so there's one
argument which is that it's a tool so it
started off being a tool and it would be
as you say it's a category mistake to
confuse the map with the territory in
this case so to confuse the tool with
the actual on the thing that exists now
that itself is not an argument against
the thing that exists
the thing exists being isomorphic to the
map the map being the of course it's
just saying it's just saying hold on
right be careful right it's just
precaution now it takes a further step
to go well actually I think that it's
nonsense that the map is the territory
and I think this goes a little bit to
what um V Vicente rajer and his
colleague spoke about that there are
certain systems at least in his
perception that it's not just the case
that the tools that we bring to bear on
these systems
um you have to be precautious when you
apply them and say that there's
something onto logic happing he's saying
that the tool is insufficient right like
whatever the tool is doing it's in no
way M there's no way we can even it
doesn't even make sense to say that
something like that is going on in the
real world and he has the example of a
candle flame right and this idea with
the candle flame is that the flickering
of it implies that this Mark of blanket
is kind of Shifting in and out of
existence there are further arguments I
mean they won't really pose as arguments
but Andy Clark's things about
metamorphosizing Mark of blanket your
own Mark of blanket super interesting
papers Mike Le's work on butterflies and
cater like questions of identity very
philosophical questions but I'm kind of
curious about how you go from saying
okay it's an instrumental tool now I
could be agnostic about how much the map
should be conflated with the territory
but it's a tool and it should be treated
as a tool and we have a different name
for what's actually going on in reality
and it might be the same thing but let's
use a different name so these are just
very scientific questions mhm it's a why
is it why did you take the further step
to say actually no it's not just that
it's a tool and we shouldn't apply it
for scientific reasons but actually the
to it it's literally not the
territory uh yeah so
um okay
so I I think there are two things I
would like to say about that so so first
would be like an intuition pump right so
so me saying that I have a that I have a
mark of
blanket would be something as ridiculous
as me saying that I have number
two what does it mean that I have number
two right so so if if you like if I tell
you I have number
two you're going to say in what way in
what sense do you have number two like
do do you mean that you you possess the
concept of number two or that you can
you know that you can calculate with
number two or you have something that is
uh that is shaped like numbered like the
Arabic numeral or I have two items that
essentially you know that's like what do
you mean by that and I think that so so
the the intuition here would be saying
that you have a mark of blanket is very
similar to to claiming that that you
have number two like it's you it cannot
be set without further qualification so
in this sense it's nonsense because you
know you have to you have to you have to
say something more you can't just stop
there so that's that's one point and now
the the second point is I
guess yeah so so so the the the the mark
of blanket trick is a is a very good
paper and I must admit that I personally
I am
not uh equipped uh in terms of my
knowledge of physics and uh modeling to
to to to to assess the that the
arguments they said that they use there
to to claim that the tool is
completely useless for the task that U
that it's supposed to do in the active
inference framework sorry but um I think
that my my and I think we would all
agree here speaking for my author my
co-authors I think that um what we would
say about this something like this so
what we would say here is
well I I we we have
demonstrated that Mark of blankets as
such are are are instruments formal
instruments that can be that do not
privilege uh between any element of the
of a graphical probabilistic model right
so every element every variable in a
probabilistic directed graphical model
can be described as having its Mark of
blanket or a mark of blanket is better
to say a mark of blanket of that
variable can be identified yeah and so
if this uh if this model does not if
this tool does not disambiguate between
or does not privilege any of the
variables in the
model that means that uh when you're
trying to when you're moving in the
realist Direction and when you're trying
to find when you're claiming that
there's a boundary in the environment
that will model and capture using this
notion it means that you're building in
some assumptions which will help you
privilege certain variables over other
variables in in your model and that's as
long as as I said before as long as
you're staying uh you know honest about
that there's nothing wrong with that
scientists do that all the time
basically building any model requires
you to say like Hey we're going to build
in some assumptions and that's
fine and now I guess what I find
troubling and and and where the
problematic jump would be is to say okay
so if you're if you're
um if you're honest about the fact that
you're building a
representation of a
certain object in the world right and
you're honest about the assumptions so
the idealizations and the kind of you
know falsities and the simplifications
that you've built into that
model if you're honest about
that it's near impossible to make the
jump into literalism and claiming that
you know like you you have to be so in
order to be a real a good realist let's
call them has to be honest about the
assumptions that go into their model and
has to be honest about the fact that you
know all models lie in a way in some way
and in order to jump from there to to
literalism you have to become a kind of
a dishonest realist so you have to you
have
to abandon you know hide all the
assumptions in order to be able to do
that
because because otherwise it's just ER
otherwise I think at least to my mind
it's it's just this kind of epistemic
jump is impossible to make if you're
taking in all the assumptions and all
the idealizations and all the
simplifications if you're stating them
explicitly in the premises and you're
clear that they are simplifications and
idealizations then it's just basically
impossible to make this final move to
claim that the map is the territory
because you just admitted that it's a
map right so so you you kind of um yeah
I so okay so yeah I understand that in
terms of a strict literalism that the
world is always too complicated in some
sense it always udes us uh and so when
we're modeling it we always have to
build in our assumptions but it still
seems to me that there's a difference
between assumptions that lie and
assumptions that
simplify right so I can I can take a
very coar grained uh model of reality
which never
nevertheless has a faithful reliable
mapping to that reality like a map right
and and so maybe I end up having a kind
of
um teleonomic analysis of my map that it
serves me right like my GPS serves me it
isn't the world but it serves me now
that seems very different from a map a
mapping which lies right a map which
says that I'm in Paris when I'm in
London now that's just to one that's
totally useless and two like it's
literally wrong it's not just that it's
a Well it's not just that it's a
compression it's a compression which in
its ISO you know which in its mapping is
wrong right I'm not saying that the
mapping I'm not saying that of course a
compression is right of course there
there's not a strict isomorphic mapping
between the map and the territory
nevertheless I still think I I'm curious
about whether you could whether you
might be open to the idea let's say that
nonetheless we build in our assumptions
they're simplifying so we can't adopt a
strict literalism
nevertheless there is a way in which we
could build out of that model that we
end up having given the assumptions that
we've had and we inflate it all and we
end up with a picture of reality like an
actual true faithful picture of reality
and that follows basian
mechanics
um okay so well it's worth I have no
invested uh usion in this game right
like I'm I'm just asking questions so
just on the table I just think this
stuff is
interesting yeah no no this is this is
this is a perfectly fine question and I
think it's it's uh great that you're
asking it it's just that I'm trying
to uh figure out you know so so so your
question basically is that um well so so
I think we have to we have to ask
ourselves what is the end goal here
maybe this is this is what we could
start with because so literalism would
be a view that kind of like in the B has
famous short story about the Empire and
the map of the Empire literalism would
be a view where the the you know you
blow up the models you you you you kind
of build that build up build up build up
build up you describe more and more
phenomena using those models and
suddenly it turns out that you've it's
the world the model it's the world
exactly so so there would be a onetoone
correspondence between the model and the
world and I think that first of all
that's not really feasible well it's not
a
model exactly it stops being a model and
then the second thing is that
um it's it stops having any use so to
speak right uh so so it becomes useless
so as as soon as the map of the Empire
spans the whole empire it's it cannot
perform its function as a map do you
think there are people the active
inference Community who think that liter
you know adopt such a radical literalism
no no no but but but I I'm sure that you
know the literature has exploded
expanded so much that I'm pretty sure
pretty sure that any position you can
imagine in that literature has been
taken by someone so sure but uh but when
it comes to the but but people do talk
about you know organisms having Mark of
blankets and I find this very puzzling
so this is just what we were attacking
this as we said earlier category mistake
now the the the interesting question
here the there's a second possibility
here which I think you're pointing to
which is that we're building we're
starting with a model of the world which
you know is not not an exact replica of
the world it's a it's a model and then
we kind of expand this model and we end
up with something that is not an exact
replica of the world because it
shouldn't be but it's is a complete
system um that corresponds in
interesting ways or in relevant ways or
some truth preserving ways to how things
are in the world so we kind of get this
this this this model that tracks things
and and in a realistic way and I think
that's uh I'm not close to this
possibility I just don't entirely see
right now how you could get there so to
speak with the with the mark of blankets
and active inference at this point in
time so one of my worries that we don't
mention in the paper I think is I don't
remember now exactly but I don't think
it's in the paper one of my worries is
that um you can have two types of
explanations right so you can have this
kind of horizontal view of explanation
where you're explaining you're covering
a huge ground and you're bringing a lot
of phenomena in under one kind of
shallow umbrella where you're creating
this kind of uh spreading structure that
connects many many often very dist disci
by using a kind of a lingua franka of of
some formalism and this seems to be the
project of of active inference right now
so there's more and more fields that are
kind of brought Under the Umbrella of
free energy more and more phenomena are
described as versions or as you know um
of ways of doing active inference and
that's very interesting it's an
interesting unificatory project where
you're trying to unify many different
branches and many different domains of
science but there's another model of
explanation in science which is not
about unification but is about vertical
integration right so you're kind of
trying to study one phenomenon on
different
scales and and you're doing it in a very
kind of narrow window uh narrow narrow
kind of uh window of focus so you're
really trying to understand how one
mechanism is realized on different
levels of organization so neuronal
spiking right for example you can study
the ion channels and then you you can
study protein folding and all these kind
of different aspects of how a neuron
operates and you're just interested in
one in one piece of the brain you're
interested in how a single neuron
responds to stimulate but you can study
that on ever more fine grain levels of
description and in the end hopefully you
have this kind of vertical integration
where you understand how the brain works
starting from a very you know s a
subcellular level onto onto the level of
the whole brain or at least an area of
the brain or a network of
neurons uh and I'm not entirely sure
that these two models of explanation are
compatible so I think that active
inference and the free energy principle
is doing an interesting interesting work
bringing in different domains of inquiry
into a common framework in which they
can start to to interact so suddenly you
know it's it it used to be the case that
people doing reinforcement learning were
very far from people doing I don't know
something like uh
phology yeah for example yeah uh or or
doing perceptual modeling and suddenly
there's a possibility that these two
people these two groups of people will
interact and will be you know talking to
each other and that's extremely
valuable however I'm not entirely sure
that the free energy principle and the
active inference stuffff is very good at
providing this kind of vertical
integration precisely because as you're
trying to describe everything using the
same tool it might turn out that on
different levels of
description there are better suited more
accurate ways of modeling things that
don't conform to the assumptions of the
free energy principle or the assumptions
of the active inference framework in
general whatever you want to call it so
there might be kind of
in different domains of inquiry kind of
these vertical domains of you know where
people are trying to study a particular
phenomenon at a ever finer level of
detail there might be domain specific or
level specific ways of modeling
certain certain phenomena or processes
which are better suited for that purpose
than the free energy formulation using
Mark of blankets and then the problem
becomes kind of that well should we
abandon that in favor of this
overarching you know structure that
connects everything I think we can be a
kind of pluralist about that so we can
we can think of the free energy
principle or the active inference
framework as this uh highlevel abstract
unifying layer while not uh diminishing
the work that's being done in very
particular uh areas and the reason sorry
just I lost track a little bit because
I'm getting tired
yeah soon but the reason why I'm not
sure that active inference can do this
vertical integration is because
precisely it's trying to redescribe
every phenomenon on every level of
finess of grain as doing the same thing
yeah and that's actually a problem right
because if you find out that a single
neuron is doing the same thing that a
that I don't know an ion channel is
doing you might be in a you might have a
problem here and I think that's that
that that's maybe my my general qualm
here yeah so I'm getting tired as well
so so we will wrap up imminently um but
there just several things that come to
mind I mean one is that I think it's
probably not the case at least in most
recent formulations that active
inference would say that the neuron is
doing the same thing as a planet it's
just that the neuron looks like it's
doing the same thing as a planet or can
be described as if it's doing the same
thing as a planet and then I guess all
of these concerns get deflated in some
ways which is which I mean look given my
again you have been in this game a lot
longer than I have but even my first
encounter of active influence is very
much being on this looks as if line so I
think we're not really going to have any
problems with that and even in your
commentary your response to the 35
people who got in touch uh you very much
say you know in response to inz and
Maxwell and Thomas vanz like we don't
really disagree like it's
instrumentalism deflates all of this I
guess the thing is right like you said
something really interesting in there
and I'm wondering whether it's a like
whether you meant to say it which is one
is that there may be tools which are
better at modeling right so I actually
hear this a lot from RL people where I
work at Royal Holloway which is active
influence is an as if it's very good
it's very interesting it's cool that you
can get from basic physics to uh a as if
physics of life like it's cool it's
interesting however uh we have to do
model comparison and if active inference
models uh better than RL then we'll use
it but if RL is better than active
influence we'll use that now that's
that's one thing and and like I think
everyone in the scientific world is
interested in that and and should
probably advocate for that because why
not right like it has better Downstream
uh effects when it comes to whatever
therapeutic goals but you also said
something that is that sometimes those
models those RL models uh again someone
can go back and check the tape but it
was something akin to and you can check
you can correct me uh it they may
actually break the assumptions of active
inference now that seems a different
problem
that's true well I guess my question
here is is it a different problem
because so if I break the Assumption of
a theory is it does it turn out that
that theory is wrong so if for example
um active inference rests on I don't
know whatever it rests on like okay it
rests on I mean maybe it does again I
think another issue here is are we
talking about the free energy principle
are we talking about active inference as
predictive processing active inference
as P active so I've actually been
thinking this in my own case
uh Act of inference is a very loose term
right when I write it I say it's a
coroller of the free energy principle
because KL says it's a COR and I know
what that means but and then they say
active influence is a process Theory I
mean that 2017 FR and paper is active
inference as a process Theory now the
free energy principle is not a process
Theory so active inferences is kind of
this weird Middle Ground of broaching
Bridging the free energy principle
predict to processing and pomdp schema
but you know that said I guess the
question is right if I take one of these
deep assumptions of active inference for
example we are doing uh there's a KL
Divergence so rather than doing Monte
Carlo sampling we use the K Divergence
if I break that do I in turn break
active inference and and how deep does
that rot
go because right like in my estimation
I've said this on this podcast Cole said
it to me the free energy principle is
quite shallow like it's very deep and
shallow in an interesting way it's
deflation
it doesn't really tell you anything that
exists and then you build out of it I'm
wondering whether you say Okay RL breaks
a core assumption I don't know what that
would look like but let's say it breaks
a core assumption um how deep does that
rot
go okay so what I was thinking about
specifically is that if you want to be a
real realist about Mark of
blankets you have to bring some
assumptions on board right so like you
you it's not like it all falls out of
using variational base you have to
assume some extra stuff and so in the
past one of these assumptions was
ergodicity I was gonna say ergodicity
yeah and so ergodicity is a good example
where if you have a model in some domain
at there was a time I don't know what it
is now because you know I've kind of
work on other stuff now so I have been
paying less attention to the development
in the literature but I know that people
have been moving away from the
ergodicity Assumption and the in the
inference literature but there's a
there's but ergodicity is a good example
because there was a time uh where
ergodicity was kind of baked in to what
people thought active inference and the
free energy principle are supposed to be
and then if you break that assumption so
if you don't have that assumption in
your model then it would seem that you
know you're you're you're breaking some
you're incompatible on a very important
assumption with with what's happening in
the what was happening at the time in
the active inference and so the question
would be then like does that
completely
invalidate your model or whether that
completely invalidates the free energy
principle and I think I would be rather
reconciliatory here by saying that you
know you don't expect all the models to
have all the same assumptions
because models are representations of
reality so what you probably want to do
is like there's some phenomenon that
you're trying to describe and the more
complex the phenomenon like life itself
the more angles you want to look at it
from so you probably want to have this
plurality of models and I think that's
that's all fine right uh the other thing
is uh and then if if you're a pluralist
in this way I guess the problem you
might encounter is that why would you
need a single principle like the free
energy principle right yes
um and
uh in that kind of raises different
questions and and again if if you're a
pluralist if you're a kind of a
perspectival list where you think that
there are multiple perspectives to look
at single phenomenon that are can be all
equally informative depending on your
explanatory interests or pragmatic
interests then I would say Well it
starts to become it starts to be
difficult to see why you would want to
claim that there's this overarching
principle yeah unless you're looking at
this Principle as just a means as I said
before of building this super structure
right which is just you know as if doing
free energy minimization story which is
supposed to create these Bridges between
very distant disciplines or domains
bringing them into together into into
conversation which is pragmatically very
valuable let's agree on that but it's
it's it might not be the be all end all
of you know science no no I mean I mean
yeah there's an interesting kind of meta
sociological point about why people want
to Gran unifying theory of anything I
mean it's it's definitely
satisfying um in some primordial sense
but beyond that it may be wise to rest
among um
plurality as you say and and there's
also the you know the argument from the
pessimistic meta induction which is that
uh every Theory up till now so we have
certain set of scientific theories we
think
are uh best right now but every theory
that preceded them in each of the fields
has been discarded as false or as you
know missing some important aspects so
why should we assume that our current
theories are true if history of science
is is you know layered with with with
husks of abandoned theories and one more
thing that I just wanted to mention you
earlier said about the incompatibility
of different theories in science and I
immediately thought about the
incompatibility of quantum mechanics and
and Newtonian mechanics and what's
interesting about that case is that even
though we don't really know how to make
the two compatible
uh we haven't abandoned either right so
there there's like there's a
possibility that you will have on
different levels of description of
reality you will have different models
with different assumptions describing
different phenomena and that's actually
okay maybe that's just how it
is yeah I I'd like to get a philosopher
philosopher science on here because I
think um this isn't really well this
isn't my era of expertise but I I think
there are slight differences between the
models that employed by the free energy
principle and the models that Newton
employed and I think one of them is that
when I write down uh f equals ma right
the of course I make the Assumption of
you know and I do that school and I they
say okay what's the acceleration of the
car and it's got this got this Mass I
then make the Assumption of uh win
resistance and um the lack of wi
resistance Tire lack of friction and
everything like but it seems to
me that in principle Newton could have
recognize those assumptions and built
them into his model and he gets a closer
approximation of the truth the question
therefore and we'll leave it here
because we been going for three hours
and a bit is whether the free energy
principle is like Newtonian mechanics
such that it can act as the base a true
ontological base because I think if you
ask Newton he would say literally f
equals ma right like it's not just I say
it and it looks as if things are doing f
equals ma it's like if I know like it's
not just if I Know M and I know a going
to know F it's like that's a law of the
universe inscribed in the universe now
I'm not a philosopher of science I'm
also not a physicist so I might be wrong
here but it seems to me that that
therefore acts as a base on which you
can build in friction you can build in
air resistance and so on and you get a
closer approximation on the truth
and that doesn't make his theory false
right because it idealizes it just makes
it a base right and it just means it's
pragmatically useful but it doesn't make
it false the real question here
therefore and I'm not going to answer it
today because I'm out of caffeine and
I'm out of energy is whether the free
and liy principle is that base as well
and I guess uh time will tell on that
front but you know I mean
ultimately epistemic humility I do think
is the way right I mean I think I think
if we can talk about one recurrent thing
that's been very useful in the history
of science is epistemic humility
plurality listening to the other side
and uh so that's why you know I very
much appreciate you coming on the show
um because well it's not a lion's den I
mean I've had viente on I've had all
sorts I've had people who don't I think
most people are partial to active
inference but it's not really a strict
active inference fan club um but no I
mean I really do appreciate the openness
and the expertise
and the dantian curiosity now it's um
it's been amazing I mean three hours and
five minutes have flown by thanks yeah
it's sorry that I wore you out uh so
much you should you should be
apologizing if you didn't wear me out um
uh yeah you just to close up you asked
me at some point who wrote the maths in
the mark of blanket paper so it was
first and foremost Manuel baltieri
because he has background in machine
learning so he knows a lot of this stuff
and then I was helping him I think that
was the that would be the correct way to
nice okay yeah always I'm always I'm
always super impressed I mean it's just
it's kind of a project that I'm trying
to undertake myself as well orbe it
having that and then simultaneously
battling the kind of fears like no this
is just an instrumental tool get back to
Consciousness get back to Consciousness
like that's for not like you know at
least that exists and so on and there's
an
interesting uh sort of pulling and you
know throwing in different directions
and I guess active inference does that
it Bridges as you say these multiple
domains but I'm very glad personally
people might disagree with me I'm very
glad that philosophers have brought to
bear their expertise um I think as you
know in the modern world we probably are
a bit disenchanted by philosophy but
actually I think with the prominence of
active inference it's kind of shown its
strength and power to say hold on a
second think about your presuppositions
think about your axioms and I'm
personally a really big fan that of the
fact that phenomenology and
Consciousness has also kind of returned
I mean it's not that you know it
returned in 1995 or you know you can go
Thomas Nagel but like this feels like a
real Renaissance of this question um so
you know Long Live philosophy I think is
the is the final note but yeah Chris
amazing I I think this much well I think
this is the longest podcast um
no no no no well Cole went no way Cole
went for about three hours Julian kinee
went for about three hours so you're
you're in good
company okay thank
you really I this was really really fun
I really enjoyed it so thank you so much
uh all right thank you so much for your
time again sorry for wearing you out
sorry if I was maybe a little bit
incoherent at times which sometimes
happens when you're going for so long uh
please send me the draft of your paper
you have my email so I would love to
read that that's very kind and also Al
uh before you leave and before we end
the show please let people know where
they can find you what you've got coming
up you'll work with ax or like anything
that you want to say in terms of
self right uh I know this horrible
everyone hates this bit but no no it's
yeah I I get it that's how it works um
so my website is Chris k r Ys
dolega
doxyz uh that's where you can kind of
track my Publications and stuff and if
you look for chriso Lega spelled in the
same way on Twitter or blue sky and
Mastadon I think that will also pop
up um and uh yeah together with Axel
we're organizing a symposium at this
year's assc in Tokyo oh nice so that's
something that uh if you're in Tokyo at
the time and visiting for the assc you
can come to it's on unconscious affect
and finally I will be also giving a talk
which will be online uh in something
called uh the Tokyo analytic philosophy
Forum uh let me just check if I remember
the date
uh I will make sure all of this is in
the uh Tokyo forum for analytic
philosophy it's it's uh series of talks
that's hosted at the Tokyo University
and I will be speaking on on the 19th of
July fantas actually about something
that we touched on briefly here so about
effective modes of presentation and
perceptual experience so yeah if you're
interested in that you can join that
will be that will be online will be
going in this will be going in the
description assc will be going in the
description I'll put the website in that
as well okay cool cool we've done three
hours and 10 minutes okay amazing thank
you so much thanks a lot have a good
evening and take care